<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<kc>

<title>Interview</title>

<author email="vinn@theshell.com">Brian Vincent</author>

<issue num="4" who="Jeremy White" date="22 April 2003" />

<intro>
<p>In the spotlight this week is Jeremy White.  Jeremy has
been involved with Wine for about six years.  However his
contributions are unique in that programming isn't what he
focuses on.</p>

<p>In 1996 Jeremy founded <a href="http://www.codeweavers.com">CodeWeavers</a>,
the creators of the popular CrossOver Office and CrossOver Plugin products.
He lives in St. Paul, Minnesota with his wife and two children.  Before
starting CodeWeavers, Jeremy founded
Holten, White and Associates, a computer consulting firm.  You may
be interested in some previous interviews with ConsultingTimes
<a href="http://www.consultingtimes.com/articles/codeweavers/codeweaversxandros.html">about
working with Xandros</a> and the Linux Weekly News 
<a href="http://lwn.net/Articles/7775/">about CodeWeavers development</a>.  

</p>
</intro>

<interview>




<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 When you started CodeWeavers, it wasn't your intention to work 
 with Wine.  How did you get involved? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
I started CodeWeavers because I wanted to do interesting 
work that mattered.  One day in 1997, I stumbled across 
the Wine project (while looking for an Atari 2600 emulator, 
but that's a different story &lt;grin&gt;).  I was immediately 
struck by the audacity of Wine, and I felt that if Wine 
could be truly successful, it would help Linux break open 
the desktop market. 
</p><p>
Of course, I have two small kids, and a day job that kept 
me very busy, so I couldn't do anything more than lurk 
on wine-devel.  But, whenever we would buy tickets for a big lottery 
jackpot, I'd always fantasize about retiring and just 
hacking on Wine. 
</p><p>
Later, I read an advice column that essentially said: 
"You have to pursue your dreams."  Of course, this was back 
in the go-go 90's, when that was easier, and back during the 
first major buzz period for Linux. 
</p><p>
So, I decided to completely reinvent the company around 
the Wine project (as well as the TWIN project, but that's 
a bit of a sideline).  Luckily, I caught Alexandre at a 
good time, and he agreed to join us, as did a number of 
the other core Wine hackers.  It was touch and go - I 
distinctly remember telling Alexandre that I wasn't sure 
I could do much more than pay his moving costs to 
the states, but we did successfully close a 
first round of funding, and hence CodeWeavers focus on 
Wine was born. 
</p></answer>






<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 How many people work at 
 CodeWeavers, and how many work on Wine development?</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
 There's about 20 people (it's a funny number; we have a number
 of part time contractors who come and go).  About 12 work
 on Wine in some way.</p></answer>



<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 Are there any Wine developers you wish worked for you but don't?</p></question>
<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
Absolutely.  And no, I'm not naming names.  But the more
people we can help to work full time on Wine,
the better, as far as I'm concerned.
There is plenty to do &lt;grin&gt;.
</p><p>
However, I am absolutely thrilled with the group
we have now.  I have never in my life worked with
as great a group of people as we currently
have at CodeWeavers.
</p></answer>


<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 The two CrossOver products seem quite successful.  Has it been 
 a little less stressful this year when it comes to financials? </p></question>


<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
2002 was a good year - not fantastic - but a good year for us.  
</p><p>
The initial reaction to CrossOver Office was phenomenal; we were very 
tight for cash, and the sales of CrossOver Office literally saved the 
company. 
</p><p>
However, we're not (yet) swimming in money; every month is still a 
struggle.  Part of that, though, is that we've all agreed to 
hang together because there is so much we want to do. 
</p><p>
I am very hopeful that 2003 will be the year we really start 
to fly.  There is <b>so much</b> I want to do on Wine this year. 
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 Anything you can share?</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
Oh gosh.  None of it's really secret.  There's the obvious:
Office XP, Access, MS Project, Photoshop, WordPerfect Office,
AutoCAD, all the Macromedia stuff, and so on.
</p><p>
Then there's the less obvious:  I really want to make
enough money that I can sponsor a Windows application
compatibility center.  The idea would be to buy up every
single title of software we could find and have a dedicated
staff that  a) tested and retested until every app installed
and came up to the main menu  and b) regression tested
each new rev of Wine to make sure it stayed that way.
So many apps are usable if you can just get 'em over the
first hump.  I want to destroy the hump.
</p><p>
Then there's performance:  get some good optimizations going,
maybe play with a kernel module.
</p><p>
I'm really excited by the game development; I think what
Lionel et all are doing is fantastic.
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 CodeWeavers has done a lot of contract work for other companies 
 interested in Wine.  What's been the most successful project 
 you've worked on? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
That's a tough one.  We've done a lot of projects over the years, 
and there have been a lot of good successes.  We really enjoyed 
MusicMatch; they were great people to work with.  Unfortunately, 
it didn't work out for them (the demand was much less than 
expected). 
</p><p>
My personal favorite is probably a small project we just 
finished for Legal Aid of Manitoba.  It was not a lot of work, 
but we helped them continue to use some legacy Win31 code 
that wouldn't work well on Windows XP.  They were great to work with, 
we were able to help them in a simple and cost effective manner 
(not always the case), and everyone is happy.  This kind 
of choice is what Wine and Free Software is all about. 
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 MusicMatch has bundled their software with tons of products.  Did
 they ever include the Linux version?  Or was it strictly for download
 only?  </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
I think they may have; they tried to move it in a variety of ways.
The honest truth, I think, is that there wasn't enough interest.
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 And are there any failures you'd care to share? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
Probably our greatest disappointment was with Corel's WordPerfect 
Office.  Corel was forced to ship that earlier than any of 
the developers liked; the product ended up with bad reviews as 
a result.  Before Corel gave up the Linux market, we had a version 
going that was *much* nicer.  It hurt to watch that wither. 
It particularly hurt because Corel was great to work with. 
</p><p>
I think that WordPerfect Office for Linux could still be 
a viable product if the timing had just worked out differently. 
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 How important was the work done by Corel?</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
They did some really great work, particularly around COM.
They also did a lot of work which helped make Winelib
a better possibility.
</p><p>
Most importantly - they gave it <b>all</b> back, with no reservations.
They were nothing but a great citizen, in my opinion.
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 Your products now come with several different distributions.  
 Are there any companies you work more closely with than 
 others?  Or do you just provide everyone with the same code 
 and let them sort it out? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
We're really still new to it; we're building a great relationship 
with both Xandros and SuSE.  However, we really want Wine 
(especially CrossOver &lt;evil grin&gt;) to become widely 
distributed and used, so we're always talking to new distributions. 
</p><p>
We do work closely with each partner to make sure it integrates 
smoothly.  Basically, the key value (beyond Wine) that we provide 
is spit and polish, and to do that right, you have to work 
with the distributions. 
</p></answer>


<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 Xandros now has Win4Lin bundled with it.  Doesn't that directly
 compete with CrossOver?  </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
Well, yes and no.  It certainly is a competitor in
many ways, but there are a good range of things
that Win4Lin does that Wine cannot (yet).  Similarly,
CrossOver integrates into the OS in some nice ways
that Win4Lin cannot.
</p><p>
I think what Xandros has done is given their customers
more options, and that's the greatest thing about
Free Software - all the choices you have.
</p></answer>


<question><p><i>BV: </i>
 You now have the server edition as well as the normal CrossOver
 Office.  Do you have a preference between corporate users versus
 home/small business users?  </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
I love our single end users; they are consistently the most
supportive and enthusiastic of our customers.  However, the reality
is that, if we thrive, we will receive a large chunk of our revenue
from corporate users.  And, in a way, helping a company to
move is even more satisfying than just helping one individual.</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 TransGaming has a unique subscription process that seems to
 focus on improving support of specific games.  How do you guys
 go about figuring out what applications to support?
 To what extent is your development driven by the customer?
</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
The honest answer is that it's currently a completely
subjective process.  We work from customer support
requests, from customer comments, and most of all,
from cases where customers commit cash to
solve a particularl problem.
</p><p>
With that said, I think TransGaming has done a nice
job with their system, and we are planning to add a voting type
of facility to our support system in the fairly
near future.</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 It seems like a lot of Wine work involves very careful reading 
 of licensing.  Do you guys keep a team of lawyers on hand to 
 review your projects? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
Well, back when we still had a lot of money, I spent a fair 
amount of money on lawyers.  These days, I'm the in house expert 
on license agreements.  And I have become far too good a student 
of Microsoft licenses.  That's a job I wouldn't wish on 
my worst enemy. 
</p></answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 If you could add one feature to Wine, what would it be? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
That's a tough one - I want to add a <b>lot</b> of features to Wine. 
This probably doesn't count as a feature, but what I really 
want to do is open a 'Wine testing center' and go buy every 
$9.99 bargain bin Windows program I can find and make every 
single one of them install and come up to the main menu.  
</p></answer>






<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 Creating Winelib apps would appear to be an important feature.  
 Do you think it will be used more or will it remain a niche 
 project? </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
You know, I'm not sure.  Winelib remains my personal passion. 
In fact, when I was new to Wine, I was equally enamoured 
of TWIN, because, at the time, it was much better at source porting 
than Wine was.  (Okay, TWIN was a mistake.  I blew it. 
But we did penance - Francois did a really nice job on winemaker, 
and really getting Winelib fixed up). 
</p><p>
However, over time, I'm gradually beginning to accept that running 
an .exe file is really no different than the same code as a 
Winelib application.  
</p><p>
So, Winelib really only becomes crucial for ports to non x86 
architectures.  Which I still think is cool, but is maybe 
a smaller part of the cool than I originally thought.  </p>
</answer>




<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 In addition to everything else, you're pretty active on the 
 CodeWeavers support mailing lists.  Does that consume a lot 
 of your time?  </p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
I don't have a problem with email.  I can quit any time.  &lt;grin&gt; 
</p><p>
I tend to answer on the support lists on the weekends, and late 
at night, when no one else is 'working'.  I particularly like 
getting involved in the beta tests. It's something I enjoy, 
but it does take a lot of time.  But I don't get to code 
anymore (see below), so what else am I gonna do? 
</p></answer>

 

<question><p><i>BV: </i> 
 How do you select people for beta testing?  Do you go through
 several cycles, or is everything pretty cleaned up by the time
 it hits beta?</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
We throw darts &lt;grin&gt;.  Seriously, we pretty much ask
for volunteers on our discussion list, and those that volunteer
get put on the beta list.  We cull the beta list of folks
that don't help out from time to time.

Initially, we tended to beta things when they were pretty
far along in the process, but lately, we've been doing
more alpha quality testing (in part due to tester demand &lt;g&gt;).
</p></answer>






 
<question><p><i>BV:</i> Final thoughts?</p></question>

<answer><p><i>Jeremy:</i> 
 Probably the greatest irony of what I'm doing is that I 
 started out with the dream of going and hacking on Wine - 
 and I never get to do any coding at all.  Instead, my 
 job is selling, business development, and administrivia. 
 And, when I submit a patch, Alexandre rejects it out of 
 hand because he doesn't like my comment style...&lt;grin&gt; 
</p><p>
 But I wouldn't trade it for anything - we're doing really cool 
 work that really matters (I just need winelauncher to 
 stick around for a while, so I can get credit for 
 <b>something</b> &lt;g&gt;). 
</p></answer>


</interview>

</kc>
