<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<kc>

<title>Kernel Cousin Wine</title>

<author email="eric.pouech@lemel.fr">Eric Pouech</author>

<issue num="22" date="20 Dec 1999 00:00:00 -0800" />

<intro>

This is the twenty second release of the Wine's kernel cousin
publication. Its main goal is to distribute widely what's
going on around Wine (the Un*x Windows emulator).

<p />

Because of Christmas holidays, there won't be any KC Wine next week.

</intro>

<stats posts="109" size="386" contrib="45" multiples="24" lastweek="23">

<person posts="10" size="53" who="Peter Ganten &lt;peter@ganten.org&gt;" />
<person posts="7" size="17" who="'Juergen Schmied' &lt;juergen.schmied@debitel.net&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="15" who="Jutta Wrage &lt;jw@witch.westfalen.de&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="8" who="Michael Cardenas &lt;Michael_Cardenas@deneba.com&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="13" who="'Sander van Leeuwen' &lt;sandervl@xs4all.nl&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="8" who="Ove Kaaven &lt;ovehk@ifi.uio.no&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="57" who="Francois Gouget &lt;fgouget@psn.net&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="13" who="Andreas Mohr &lt;amohr@student.ei.uni-stuttgart.de&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="11" who="'Dmitry Timoshkov' &lt;dmitry@sloboda.ru&gt;" />

</stats>

<section
  title="Buffers Handling"
  subject="Buffers handling"
>

Francois Gouget had a hard time trying to fix (from crashes and also
code re-reading) some potential buffer overflows, missing trailing
'\0' on strings and strncpy vs lstrncpyA (the later always add a
trailing '\0', whereas the former doesn't if the destination buffer is
too small). Francois provided several patches for review, which
J&#252;rgen Schmied and Andreas Mohr commented. Francois also sent a tool
to help tracking those issues (which has been added to the unofficial
patches list).

</section>

<section
  title="Crypto APIs and US laws"
  subject="Crypto APIs and US laws"
  archive="http://www.integrita.com/cgi-local/lwgate.pl/WINE-DEVEL/archives/1999-12/Subject/article-293.html"
>

Shaun Morris had some concerns with implementing Windows cryptographic
APIs:

<quote who="Shaun Morris">Would there be any problem with implementing the functions of the
CryptoAPI (CryptAcquireContext, etc.) in advapi, from an NSA knocking
down my door perspective?  Obviously, Microsoft has done it, and the
actual crypto goes in the provider, but I'm still a little concerned.</quote>

<p />

Chet Murphy provided a faq (from the Mozilla project) describing the
details of cryptographic APIs and exportation rules from the US:
<a href="http://www.mozilla.org/crypto-faq.html">
http://www.mozilla.org/crypto-faq.html</a>

<p />

Alexandre Julliard gave his view on the subject:

<quote who="Alexandre Julliard">I am not going to include in the standard distribution any patch that
would cause Wine to fall under export restrictions. Besides I'm living
in the US now so I wouldn't even be allowed to distribute the releases
if I did include such a patch...

<p />

If there are really APIs that fall under export restrictions, they
need to be developed and distributed from outside the US, as a patch
to the main release. And you have to be very careful that nobody
residing in the US takes any part in the development.</quote>

<p />

At the end of this thread, it was still not clear if the highest
CryptoAPI was falling under the US export restriction (the lowest
layer, of course, is).

</section>

</kc>
