<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.theshell.com/~vinn">Brian Vincent</author>
<issue num="262" date="02/18/2005" />
<intro> <p>This is the 262nd issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to ponder beaches. It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="267" size="937" contrib="86" multiples="48" lastweek="29">

<person posts="14" size="43" who="Oliver Stieber" />
<person posts="13" size="41" who="Mike Hearn" />
<person posts="11" size="56" who="Jeremy White" />
<person posts="10" size="33" who="Dmitry Timoshkov" />
<person posts="10" size="24" who="Alexandre Julliard" />
<person posts="9" size="37" who="Robert Reif" />
<person posts="9" size="30" who="Paul Vriens" />
<person posts="8" size="61" who="Holly Bostick" />
<person posts="8" size="24" who="Scott Ritchie" />
<person posts="8" size="23" who="Francois Gouget" />
<person posts="7" size="24" who="Francois Gouget" />
<person posts="7" size="24" who="James Hawkins" />
<person posts="7" size="20" who="Ivan Leo Puoti" />
<person posts="6" size="22" who="Marcelo Duarte" />
<person posts="6" size="19" who="Robert Shearman" />
<person posts="6" size="18" who="Tom" />
<person posts="6" size="17" who="Mike McCormack" />
<person posts="5" size="20" who="(cyrix12)" />
<person posts="5" size="18" who="Paul Millar" />
<person posts="4" size="16" who="Jesse Allen" />
<person posts="4" size="12" who="Paul van Schayck" />
<person posts="4" size="11" who="Maxime Bellenge" />
<person posts="3" size="12" who="Steven Edwards" />
<person posts="3" size="10" who="Hans Leidekker" />
<person posts="3" size="9" who="Jonathan Ernst" />
<person posts="3" size="9" who="Shachar Shemesh" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Thomas Weidenmueller" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Dietrich Teickner" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Andreas Mohr" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Joris Huizer" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Rein Klazes" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Ira Krakow" />
<person posts="2" size="14" who="Alex Woods" />
<person posts="2" size="10" who="Rolf Kalbermatter" />
<person posts="2" size="9" who="Roderick Colenbrander" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="Duane Clark" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="Rolf Kalbermatter" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="Michael Jung" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="Rainer Haake" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Jakob Eriksson" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Boaz Harrosh" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Vincent B&#233;ron" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Filip Navara" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Marcus Meissner" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Mike Hearn" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Krzysztof Foltman" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Vitaliy Margolen" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Jonathan Wilson" />
<person posts="1" size="10" who="Tony Lambregts" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Ivan Gyurdiev" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Raphael" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Eric Pouech" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Crestez Leonard" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Sam Lauber" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Damian Dimmich" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Carl Sopchak" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Christian Costa" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Udo Rader" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Uwe Bonnes" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Jason Edmeades" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Andreas Eckstein" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Andreas Eckstein" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Lionel Ulmer" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Alexander Gottwald" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Thomas J Fogal" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Chris Morgan" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Tony Lambregts" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Paul Vriens" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Geoff Hart" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Michael Stefaniuc" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Nick Hornback" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="David Laight" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Ge van Geldorp" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Hiji" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Grant Williamson" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Vitaliy Margolen" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Zane Wickham" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="luis lenders" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Carlos Lozano" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Boaz Harrosh" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Brian Vincent" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dan Kegel" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Paul Rupe" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Scott W Gifford" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Gabriele Giorgetti" />

</stats>
<section
        title="News: Microsoft Looks for Wine"
        subject="News"
        archive="http://linux.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/02/17/1318212&amp;tid=125&amp;tid=109&amp;tid=106"
        posts="1"
        startdate="02/12/2005"
	enddate="02/18/2005"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>Slashdot covered a story that first appeared on wine-devel and
WineHQ about Microsoft checking for Wine.  The 
<a href="http://linux.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/02/17/1318212&amp;tid=125&amp;tid=109&amp;tid=106">Slashdot story</a> read:</p>
<quote who="Slashdot"><p>
<a href="http://navi.cx/~mike/">IamTheRealMike</a> writes <i>"In January, 
<a href="http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2005/jan05/01-26GenuineAdvantagePR.asp">Microsoft announced a new anti-piracy initiative</a> called
Genuine Advantage. From this summer onwards all users of <a href="http://downloads.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Downloads</a>
will be required to validate using either an ActiveX control
or a standalone tool. Yesterday Ivan Leo Puoti, a Wine developer, 
<a href="http://winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0441.html">discovered
that the validation tool checks directly for Wine</a> and bails 
out with a generic error when found. This is significant as it's
not only the first time Microsoft has actively discriminated 
against users running their programs via Wine, but it's also 
the first time they've broken radio silence on the project."</i>
</p></quote>

<p>Well, that's a pretty good summary of the news.  The actual
thread is covered in the next section, so we'll save the
details for that.  Surprisingly, most of the armchair lawyers
stayed at home and didn't ponder some of the ramifications.
</p><p>
As far as Wine is concerned, Microsoft certainly chose an
interesting time to try this out.  In the past, several 
free downloads such as DCOM and MSI were necessary to get
a lot of apps to install and run.  However, work is progressing
at a phenomenal rate in both of those areas.  By the time
this tool is required, Wine's own builtin versions will be
more than adequate.</p><p>
It sure is nice to be noticed.</p>

</section>

<section
        title="Microsoft's Wine Check: Details"
        subject="Microsoft genuine downloads looking for wine"
        archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0441.html"
        posts="14"
        startdate="02/16/2005"
	enddate="02/18/2005"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>What spawned the news above originated with a post from
Ivan Leo Puoti:</p>
<quote who="Ivan Leo Puoti"><p>
As some of you may know, Microsoft is planning to totally restrict 
access to the Microsoft download center to all non-genuine Windows 
users. So you would expect some check for pirated copies of Windows 
to be involved. If you visit the download center with IE you get an 
ActiveX control, but if you try with Firefox, you'll have to download
a little program, that returns a code you have to copy into
the download page, to get access to the download you selected.
</p><p>
By quickly looking at the program, I noticed it looks for a registry 
key, this key is...
<ul><code>SOFTWARE\Wine\Wine\Config</code></ul></p><p>
the Wine configuration key.
</p><p>
The Windows Genuine Advantage program press release
<ul><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2005/jan05/01-26GenuineAdvantagePR.asp">
http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2005/jan05/01-26GenuineAdvantagePR.asp</a></ul>
</p><p>
says that in the second half of 2005, all users connecting to the 
Microsoft download center or to Windows update
will have to validate their copy of Windows. Interestingly if you run 
the validation program on wine, and the version of windows you're 
emulating is prior to 2000 or is windows server 20003, you get a 
message saying a validation code couldn't be found, because of 
technical difficulties or because you're running an unsupported
operating system.  If you set winver to win2000, you'll get a 
validation code that doesn't work, this may be a bug in wine, or 
in the validation program. A valid and working code is returned 
if the version is set to XP.
</p><p>
Still, even if this is only an initial attempt, they
appear to want to discriminate Wine users, while this may be acceptable 
for operating system components/updates, this is probably a violation
of anti-trust law for all other downloads. 
</p><p>
It's also the first time Microsoft acknowledges the existence of Wine.
</p></quote>

<p>Ivan provided a link showing the Wine registry key in the
executable and provided an MD5 hash of the program: 
05499eaa4d4f55af32f5b14561ee7e55.  Other developers verified
they found the same thing.  You should try it too; it's fun
for the whole family.</p>
<p>Shachar Shemesh noted that it would be relatively simple to
work around the problem.  Mike Hearn thought it would be a waste
of time:</p>
<quote who="Mike Hearn"><p>
I don't think we want to go there. I demonstrated a way of checking for
Wine to Rob last night that we really cannot fix or workaround, and if I
can think of it they certainly can too.
</p><p>
Basically if we start integrating workarounds into Wine, it'll lead to an
arms race we cannot possibly win. Better to ensure our users don't need
anything from that website.
</p></quote>

<p>And now, back to our regularly scheduled program of Wine development
news.</p>

</section>

<section 
	title="COM &amp; InstallShield" 
	subject="Re: working installshield?"
	archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0342.html" 
	posts="3"
	startdate="02/14/2005"
>
<topic>RPC / COM / OLE</topic>
<p>Marcus Meissner wanted to know exactly when the huge COM rewrite will
wrap up.  Or rather, when it will make a lot of things work again:</p>
<quote who="Marcus Meissner"><p>
 Is there any chance to have a working installshield at some time?
</p><p> 
 I don't really want to fall back to the December or even earlier WINE
 releases for our spring SUSE Linux product ;)</p></quote>

<p>
Mike Hearn gave a quick update on where things were at:</p>
<quote who="Mike Hearn"><p>
Rob has a patch that should (touch wood) fix the remaining issues. I'm 
not sure when he is going to submit it but it looked pretty complete 
last time I saw it.
</p><p>
We may also need to adjust the RPC runtime so that it runs a message 
loop (for re-entrancy), but I don't think that'd be too hard.
</p><p>
So, maybe a week or two? It certainly should not be broken for more than a
month.</p></quote>

<p>Rob followed up a few hours later with the patch:</p>
<quote who="Robert Shearman"><p>

This patch is significant as it changes the RPC backend of our COM 
implementation from using named pipes to using any transport implemented 
by the RPC runtime. As a matter of coincidence, this patch is numbered 
69, which is my favourite number, and this patch is my favourite patch. 
This is because it is one of the last steps in getting our architecture 
right and consistent with the way the native version does.
Not only this, but it should also solve some real problems with having 
way too many threads (one and only one per apartment) and some complex 
deadlocking situations caused by this. It also significiantly reduces 
the amount of code in the file and reduces most of it to simple wrappers 
around the RPC runtime functions.
</p><p>
Diffstat:
</p><p><ul>
<table>
 <tr><td>compobj.c        </td><td> |   </td><td> 2</td></tr>
 <tr><td>compobj_private.h </td><td>|   </td><td> 6</td></tr>
 <tr><td>marshal.c         </td><td>|   </td><td> 3</td></tr>
 <tr><td>rpc.c             </td><td>| </td><td>1001 </td></tr>
 <tr><td colspan="3">+++++++++++++++++++-----------------------------------</td></tr>
 <tr><td>stubmanager.c     </td><td>|   </td><td> 4</td></tr>
 <tr><td colspan="3">5 files changed, 369 insertions(+), 647 deletions(-)</td></tr>
</table></ul></p><p>
Changelog:
<ul>
Make COM use the RPC runtime as the backend for RPC calls. Based on a 
patch by Ove K&#229;ven.</ul></p></quote>

<p>Rob verified Mike's initial observation about needing a message loop
as well as gave Marcus a solution if things weren't worked out:</p>
<quote who="Robert Shearman"><p>
  I haven't been testing against InstallShield for a while, but last time 
  I checked it was hanging because we do not process window messages 
  during RPCs. If you want to implement this yourself, I can give you 
  details on how to do this. I will get around to this eventually, but at 
  the moment I have other priorities. If the worst happens and 
  InstallShield is still not working, then you can still ship the December 
  ole32 with the most recent Wine.</p></quote>

</section>
<section
        title="DirectX 9 and HalfLife2"
        subject="Halflife II"
        archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0513.html"
        posts="28"
        startdate="02/18/2005"
>
<topic>Build Process</topic>
<p>A long thread about <i>World of Warcraft</i> came up
this week.  I won't go into much of the details of that
one, but if you're a WoW fan you may way to
<a href="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0391.html">read
the thread</a>.  In the course of the discussion, Jonathan Wilson
asked,
<quote who="Jonathan Wilson">
 Also, how does the work we have here in this project
 compare to what  TransGaming have as far as Direct3D 
 functionality?
</quote></p>

<p>Oliver Stieber gave a ran through the status:</p>
<quote who="Oliver Stieber"><p>
on the downside..
<ul>
<li>Shaders aren't working yet, but the DirectX 8 shaders
can be migrated reasonably easily.</li>

<li>Stencil buffers aren't working properly either, which
affects shadows and odd shaped windows etc...</li>

<li>Offscreen textures aren't working fully.</li></ul>
</p><p>
on the up side.
<ul>
<li>Stateblock support seems to be more complete than
TransGaming's.</li>

<li>Swapchains are working, TransGaming doesn't have them.</li>

<li>Non-power of two textures should work on all opengl
video cards, transgaming only supports a subset of
cards.</li>

<li>Querys are stubbed, and I've got a version of
Occlusion query to test (but I think ATI's drivers are
broken), occlusion queries may give fairly large
performance increases in some games.</li>

<li>A few other minor things like point sprites are
working.</li></ul></p><p>

With the exception of a few areas performance is
on-par with cedega.
</p><p>
I'm looking at offscreen surfaces soon.
</p><p>
There are lots of easy performance boosters that can
be implemented at some point.
</p><p>
Of the games I've tested this version works more often
than Cedega, but that doesn't mean too much since most
games are failing with non DirectX related issues.
</p><p>
I've been developing with an ATI graphics card, so
there shouldn't be the odd dropout because of ATI
driver bugs that happens with Cedega. 
</p></quote>

<p>Oliver went on to describe an area he may
focus on:</p>
<quote who="Oliver Stieber"><p>
 I'm not sure what I'm going to work on next, possibly
 more 'completeness' and performance in DirextX 9 to
 give applications a good chance of running as well as
 games, or maybe some d3dx9 work so that winelib can
 compile more DirextX 9, or maybe try getting
 Microsoft's new GUI, Avalon, working under Wine.
 <ul><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=C8F904E1-B4CA-402B-ACCF-AAA2BD60DA74&amp;displaylang=en">
 http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=C8F904E1-B4CA-402B-ACCF-AAA2BD60DA74&amp;displaylang=en</a></ul></p></quote>
 
 <p>Andi Mohr wondered why that should be a target:</p>
 <quote who="Andreas Mohr"><p>
 I'm certainly not authorized to tell you what to do,
but what benefit would Avalon bring us?
It's not even really released, i.e. its applicability
should be very limited.
</p><p>
OTOH almost perfect support for DX9 games would be MUCH
more useful IMHO, since lack of gaming support is the #1 reason
for many people for not being able to switch to Linux...
</p><p>
Thanks for the incredible work so far!
</p></quote>

<p>Oliver explained why he wanted to look into it:</p>
<quote who="Oliver Stieber"><p>
Avalon depends heavily on DirectX 9, I'm not out to do
TransGaming out of work so I'd prefer to focus on what
isn't currently supported by Cedega/CrossOver Office,
this would be things like DirectX 9 applications, and
games that aren't FPS's or RTS's.
</p><p>
If Half Life 2 happens to work so be it, but I'm even
less a fan of DRM/steam then I am of duplicating
TransGaming's work.
</p><p>
If you would like me to work on something just ask. (I
have to get a Job soon though, so my output will drop
quite a bit!)</p></quote>

<p>Oliver is maintaining a website dedicated to
<a href="http://www.oliverthered.f2s.com/projects/wine/">his 
DirectX 9 work</a>.  If you're into testing bleeding 
edge patches, you'll be overjoyed.  The screenshots
are pretty cool too.  </p>

<p>Roderick Colenbrander tried out the latest patch
from Oliver's website and reported:</p>
<quote who="Roderick Colenbrander"><p>
The past few weeks I have been experimenting a bit with Wine's d3d9. After new 
updates appeared in cvs I tried games like halife2. Yesterday I tried (a 
cracked) halflife2 and cstrike:source again using Oliver's latest d3d9 patch 
and it now shows stuff! For shots check 
<ul><li><a href="http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/hl2.png">http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/hl2.png</a></li>
<li><a href="http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/cstrike.png">http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/cstrike.png</a></li></ul></p>
<p>
Both games come to the menu screens I think (not sure what it all has to look 
like) but from then on not much happens. In the case of halfife2 I see some birds 
flying on the background so the game isn't stuck. I think the menus aren't 
drawn and I guess that might be related to the fixme 
"<tt>d3d:IWineD3DDeviceImpl_SetSamplerState out of range sampler 0</tt>" which I'm 
seeing hundreds of times.
</p><p>
I'm amazed with the progress made on the d3d9 front. During the weekend I will 
try to get halflife2 working on Windows to see what it has to look like and I 
might also have time to fix this problem if it is trivial.  Just wanted to 
let you know that some major d3d9 game is now starting to work.
</p></quote>

<p>Roderick replied to himself a few minutes later with an update:</p>
<quote who="Roderick Colenbrader"><p>
Did some more experiments and the game is also playable! The issue regarding 
the menu is that some font isn't showing up, the same problem appears in the 
halflife2 console. After some fiddling I loaded a save game from the hl2 
console and it loaded the game.
</p><p>
For a screenshot check 
<a href="http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/hl2-2.png">http://roderick.student.utwente.nl/hl2-2.png</a>
</p><p>
Haven't looked at the performance yet, it is not slow guess 20-30fps or more. 
Note that this is using a radeon9000Mobility and further options like 
-dxlevel 50/60/70/80/90 might help tweaking performance in hl2. Further I 
don't know how fast/slow this game is on Windows.
</p></quote>
<p>Stop drooling, Newman.</p>

</section>

<section 
	title="Window Management Problems" 
	subject="A call to fix the BeginPaint issue"
	archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0307.html" 
	posts="6"
	startdate="02/12/2005"
	enddate="02/15/2005"
>
<topic>Graphics</topic>
<p>The window management changes have caused a few problems.  It's not
entirely clear the extent of what's going on.  Nick Hornback voiced some
frustration this week:</p>

<quote who="Nick Hornback"><p>
Alright, this is probably the last time I will bring
it up before I realize that there is essentially no
interest in fixing this, but this has been bothering
me for quite some time now. A few others have brought
it up over the past couple months as well.
</p><p>
<ul><a href="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-cvs/2004/10/0395.html">
http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-cvs/2004/10/0395.html</a></ul></p>
<p>
As discussed (but nothing really done about it), this
patch is directly known to break painting in at least
the following applcations:
<ul>
<li>DeusEx</li>
<li>Trickstyle</li>
<li>Foobar2000</li>
<li>Zoo Tycoon 1 demo</li>
</ul></p><p>

This is because, as far as I'm aware, these
applications don't send BeginPaint/EndPaint as they
technically should, but they all work fine on native
Windows. Now, before, it has simply been a matter of
reversing the patch, no big deal. However, since the
region handling has been moved to the server, that is
not possible without a lot of tinkering, something
that I just don't have the mad skillz to do.
</p></quote>

<p>Alexandre asked for some help tracking down the
issues, 
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
There is a lot of interest in fixing it, but it's far from trivial
especially for apps that I don't have. You can help by posting traces
(+server,+win,+message is usually a good start) of the offending
behavior.</quote></p>


<p>Rein Klazes explained a little more about the problem
as well as provided a link to an application that was
having the same issue.  Paul Vriens wondered if a different
issue that had been reported had the same root cause.  
Alexandre explained one of the differences between Wine
and Windows in this area, 
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
there are a number of cases where redraws are
synchronous on Windows and there are some apps that depend on that. It
wasn't done that way in Wine mostly because it caused a lot of
unnecessary refreshes, but now that we no longer get expose events on
child windows we can move towards more synchronous behavior.</quote></p>

<p>Another issue involves minimizing Windows.  Lauri
Tulmin posted a patch to the X11 driver to address the problem,
but Vitaliy Margolen reported new problems:</p> 
<quote who="Vitaliy Margolen"><p>
Ok, that semi-helps. Now I don't have an extra window that was showing up after
minimize. But programs still don't want to stay minimized. They blink in the
task bar and immediately restore themselves. Any suggestions where could it be?
</p><p>
People have commented on this before. To reiterate: all programs (that I have)
behave in this manner, not staying minimized.
</p><p>
BTW one side effect of this patch - application icon is not displayed in the
task bar anymore. Now it's back to wine's logo.

</p></quote>



</section>
<section 
	title="Drive Detection"
	subject="Re: winecfg: various drive detection enhancements"
	archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0356.html" 
	posts="5"
	startdate="02/11/2005"
>
<topic>Configuration</topic>
<p>Some patches came in this week for Wine's configuration
tool, winecfg.  For those of you just joining us, winecfg
is set to take over Wine's configuration settings and
provide an easy interface for making the changes.  It's
been in the plans for a couple of years now.  This week
some patches came in for winecfg from Michael Jung.  This
follows on the heels of drive detection support that has been
added to winecfg.  The first was a bugfix followed by some 
more significant ones:</p>
<quote who="Michael Jung"><p>
Changelog:<ul>
 Set pointers to NULL in delete_drive to prevent heap corruption in 
load_drives</ul></p><p>

Changelog:
<ul>
 Include config.h to reenable reading /etc/fstab on platforms that support it.
 Implemented a black list of mount directories, which should not be mapped.
 Ensure that the user's home directory is mapped.

</ul></p><p>
Changelog:
<ul>
 Added support for command line parameter '/D' to do drive detection from 
wineprefixcreate
</ul></p></quote>

<p>Paul van Schayck asked:</p>
<quote who="Paul van Schayck"><p>

I was just about to send a patch doing almost exactly the same things.
Including the fix you put in to properly add a drive letter to the
working_mask.
</p><p>
And are we ready to let wineprefixcreate use winecfg? Or do we want
more testing of the autodetect code?

</p></quote>

<p>Michael went ahead and posted 
<a href="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/att-0359/01-wineprefixcreate.diff">a 
small patch</a> that actually called the
new drive detect code from wineprefixcreate.  (Wineprefixcreate
is the script responsible for setting up a new Wine user's 
configuration.)  After processing the wine.inf script to set up
the registry, Michael just added  one line to call the drive
detection code.  Alexandre committed all the patches except the
last one to actually call it.  Michael asked for people to please
test it out and make sure it works.</p> 


</section>
<section
        title="distcc Patch"
        subject="Re: distcc and wine-installer"
        archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0525.html"
        posts="1"
        startdate="02/18/2004"
>
<topic>Build Process</topic>
<p>Does Wine compile too slow for you?  Do you have access
to some other machines?  Damian Dimmich posted a patch for 
integrating distcc support into the wineinstall script:</p>
<quote who="Damian Dimmich"><p>
 Just made 
 <a href="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/att-0525/01-wineinstall_distcc.diff">a
 little patch</a> to the wine installer script which allows the user
 to specify a commandline flag to enable distcc support (using 
 <tt>--distcc</tt>).
</p><p>
 This makes compiling loads faster if you have more than one machine to
 compile on.
</p><p>
 Let me know if it does not work for you.
</p></quote>

</section>

<section 
	title="LQ Members Choice Awards" 
	subject="Wine, CrossOver wins LQ Members Choice awards 2004"
	archive="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2005/02/0267.html" 
	posts="3"
	startdate="02/11/2005"
>
<p>
Mike Hearn reported the results of a LinuxQuestions poll:</p>
<quote who="Mike Hearn">
<p>
Hey, we won by a large margin!
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions/showthread.php?s=&amp;threadid=272137">
http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions/showthread.php?s=&amp;threadid=272137</a>
</p><p><ul><table>
<tr><td>Wine  </td><td>	 		293</td><td>  	42.59%</td></tr>
<tr><td>CrossOver Office </td><td>	139 </td><td>	20.20%</td></tr>
<tr><td>Cedega 	</td><td>		131 </td><td>	19.04%</td></tr>
<tr><td>VMware 	</td><td>		101 </td><td>	14.68%</td></tr>
<tr><td>Win4lin </td><td>		 24 </td><td>	3.49%</td></tr>
</table></ul>
</p><p>
Good going chaps and chapettes! Nice also to see the results are ranked 
in rough order of "freeness" too.
</p><p>
Let's see if we can win again in the 2005 voting :)
</p></quote>

<p>So, the actual category Wine won in was titled, 
<i>Windows on Linux App of the Year</i></p>.  

</section></kc>
