<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>


<title>Kernel Cousin Wine</title>

<author email="vinn@theshell.com">Brian Vincent</author>

<issue num="126" date="06/13/2002" />

<intro>
<p>
This is the 126th release of the Wine's kernel cousin publication. Its main 
goal is to distribute widely what's going on around Wine (the Un*x Windows 
emulator). </p>

</intro>






<stats posts="356" size="1425" contrib="56" multiples="37" lastweek="32">

<person posts="69" size="365" who="Deven T. Corzine &lt;deven@ties.org&gt;" />
<person posts="23" size="80" who="Matt Seitz &lt;mseitz@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="21" size="101" who="Roger Fujii &lt;rmf@lookhere.com&gt;" />
<person posts="20" size="85" who="Patrik Stridvall &lt;ps@leissner.se&gt;" />
<person posts="18" size="73" who="Martin Wilck &lt;Martin.Wilck@Fujitsu-Siemens.com&gt;" />
<person posts="17" size="54" who="Roland &lt;roland@netquant.com.br&gt;" />
<person posts="15" size="50" who="Sean C. Farley &lt;scf@farley.org&gt;" />
<person posts="14" size="64" who="Francois Gouget &lt;fgouget@free.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="12" size="28" who="Andriy Palamarchuk &lt;apa3a@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="11" size="63" who="Shachar Shemesh &lt;wine-devel@sun.consumer.org.il&gt;" />
<person posts="11" size="32" who="Tony Lambregts &lt;tony_lambregts@telusplanet.net&gt;" />
<person posts="10" size="30" who="John Alvord &lt;jalvo@mbay.net&gt;" />
<person posts="9" size="38" who="Anthony Taylor &lt;tony@paperdove.org&gt;" />
<person posts="8" size="19" who="Alexandre Julliard &lt;julliard@winehq.org&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="18" who="Vincent Beron &lt;vberon@mecano.gme.usherb.ca&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="26" who="Steve Langasek &lt;vorlon@dodds.net&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="16" who="list@vmn.com.br" />
<person posts="5" size="15" who="Ove Kaaven &lt;ovehk@ping.uio.no&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="13" who="Andreas Mohr &lt;andi@rhlx01.fht-esslingen.de&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="13" who="Marcus Meissner &lt;marcus@jet.franken.de&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="12" who="Medland, Bill &lt;Bill.Medland@accpac.com&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="13" who="Paul Millar &lt;paulm@astro.gla.ac.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="20" who="Won Kyu Park &lt;wkpark@chem.skku.ac.kr&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="15" who="Dmitry Timoshkov &lt;dmitry@baikal.ru&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="14" who="Marco Pietrobono &lt;pietrobo@pietrobo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="13" who="Greg Alexander &lt;yakovlev@mac.com&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="11" who="juergen.schmied@debitel.net" />
<person posts="3" size="10" who="Ann and Jason Edmeades &lt;us@the-edmeades.demon.co.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Brett Glass &lt;brett@lariat.org&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Johan Gill &lt;johane@lysator.liu.se&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Uwe Bonnes &lt;bon@elektron.ikp.physik.tu-darmstadt.de&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="13" who="Con Hennessy &lt;CP.Hennessy@iname.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="List vmn &lt;list@vmn.com.br&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Steven Edwards &lt;steven_ed4153@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Sylvain Petreolle &lt;spetreolle@yahoo.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="max &lt;max@veneto.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Jeremy Newman &lt;jnewman@codeweavers.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Malte Cornils &lt;malte@cornils.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Steven Edwards &lt;Steven_Ed4153@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Gavriel State &lt;gav@transgaming.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="mfeitosa &lt;mfeitosa@vmn.com.br&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="David D. Hagood &lt;wowbagger@sktc.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Bob La Quey &lt;boblq@cox.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Carl Sopchak &lt;carl.sopchak@cegis123.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Phil Bordelon &lt;phil@athar.ocs.lsu.edu&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="John K. Hohm &lt;jhohm@acm.org&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Michal Seliga &lt;michal.seliga@visicom.sk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="degs &lt;lists@giantblob.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="P. Christeas &lt;p_christ@hol.gr&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Christian Costa &lt;titan.costa@wanadoo.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Brian Vincent &lt;vinn@theshell.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Rizsanyi Zsolt &lt;rizsanyi@myrealbox.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Shachar Shemesh &lt;sun@consumer.org.il&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Hetz Ben Hamo &lt;hetz@kde.org&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="JJ Neff &lt;jjneff@yahoo.com&gt;" />

</stats>


<section
  title="News: Updated CodeWeavers' Products, Quickstart Guide"
  subject="News"
  archive="http://www.codeweavers.com/about/press_releases/?id=20020611"
  posts="2"
  startdate="06/07/2002"
  enddate="06/13/2002"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>It seems some of the scripts I've written are working out
pretty good - I'm finally putting the "Weekly" back in "Wine
Weekly News".  But don't get too used to it, I have a basement
that needs drywalling and a deck to put in.</p>

<p>CodeWeavers released updated versions of both CrossOver Plugin
and CrossOver Office.  CrossOver Plugin is now at version 1.1.2.
For the most part it looks to be just a bugfix release.  CrossOver
Office 1.1, however, is more exciting.  From the 
 <a href="http://www.codeweavers.com/about/press_releases/?id=20020611">press release</a>:</p>
<quote who="CodeWeavers"><p>
    With Version 1.1, CodeWeavers is officially supporting both 
 Microsoft Outlook and Internet Explorer, in addition to the 
 already-supported Microsoft Word, Excel and PowerPoint, and 
 IBM Lotus Notes. This enables organizations to make the 
 transition to a Linux desktop without having to completely 
 replace their internal systems. "With Outlook and Internet 
 Explorer support, we feel that we have rounded out the most 
 important features of the Microsoft Office Suite, and have 
 made it simple and painless for an organization to adopt 
 the Linux desktop" said Jeremy White, founder and CEO of 
 CodeWeavers.</p>
</quote>

<p>Also noted is improved font rendering and better internationalization.
</p>

<p>An alternate <a href="http://linuxtoday.com/news_story.php3?ltsn=2002-06-11-018-26-NW-DT-SW">
press release</a> made it's way to LinuxToday.  See if you can 
spot the two interesting paragraphs.</p>

<p>A few months ago I plugged a website - 
<a href="http://franksworld.net/wine/">Frank's World</a>.  Well,
it seems to be doing pretty good.  There's some new updates on
there and a really nice <a href="http://www.franksworld.net/wineguide/">
Quickstart Guide</a>.</p>

</section>





<section
  title="TransGaming Releasing Code"
  subject="TransGaming and ReWind"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-license/2002/06/0156.html"
  posts="2"
  startdate="06/07/2002"
>
<topic></topic>
<p>About twelve hours after I kicked issue #126 out the door 
Gav wrote to the wine-license list:</p>
<quote who="Gavriel State"><p>
 Hi everyone,
</p><p>
The past several months have seen a dramatic change in Wine's license, and
TransGaming, like many others organizations, has had to take the time to consider
how the license changes impact us, our subscribers, and our partners. We have
also taken the time to listen carefully to the comments on the Wine-License
list, and those we have received in private emails.  Ultimately, we have a
responsibility to make pragmatic business decisions that will ensure the
continued growth of our company while also preserving the interests of our
supporters.
</p><p>
In an endeavour to bring a halt to the ongoing contention regarding the
license change, we have decided to concentrate our efforts on the ReWind tree.
We hope that developers who recognize the value of the contributions we have made
and are continuing to make will support us by making their patches available to
ReWind under the X11 license.
</p><p>
Over the next few days, we will be merging a number of contributions into ReWind,
including those that were initially offered for trade, as well as some things
that were not previously offered.  Some of the more exciting bits are the DIB
engine that we've been developing, as well as our new DCOM architecture.  The
new DCOM work eliminates many of the problems that the previous typelib-only
marshalling in both WineX and Wine had.  It supports inter-thread marshalling,
and will support application defined (non-typelib-based) marshallers, in addition
to the previous OLE Automation (typelib) marshallers. It also includes a preliminary
IDL compiler that is currently suitable for automatically building Wine-style COM
macro definitions from IDL.  The IDL compiler won't actually output marshalling
bytecode yet, however.
</p><p>
The new DCOM system is still a work in progress, and we are a little ways away
from fully supporting InstallShield 6 with it.  We hope that anyone interested
in DCOM and OLE support will work with us to improve it.  There are several things
that remain to be done (including the marshalling bytecode interpreter) that Ove
will elaborate on shortly.
</p><p>
Until the ReWind (and WineX) trees have better DLL separation support, TransGaming
will not be able to directly participate in any LGPLed development, due to the
legal and business considerations that we've discussed before.  Other developers
are of course free to integrate the work that we are contributing to ReWind into
the LGPLed Wine tree.
</p><p>
We will be working on DLL separation in the ReWind tree in order to be able to take
part in LGPLed development on a component by component basis in the future.  Any
assistance offered by other developers would be appreciated, including the
re-licensing of patches that are currently LGPL-only.  Without any help, it may
be some time before we are able to share any of our work directly with the
Wine tree.
</p><p>
We are continuing our participation in the development of ReWind and Wine to the
extent that our legal and business situation allows, and we are doing everything in
our power to offer Linux gamers the best possible solution for running the games
they want on the platform they love.  We greatly appreciate the support of not
only our subscribers and supporters, but of all the individuals and organizations
who have contributed to Wine over the years.  Through our joint efforts so far, we
have been able to bring hundreds of Windows games to Linux users' desktops, and
TransGaming has been able to contribute tens of thousands of lines of code to
the Wine project.  We look forward to continued collaboration.
</p><p>
Thanks,<br /><ul>
      -Gav</ul>
</p></quote>

<p>Lionel Ulmer, one of the first people to work on DirectX in Wine,
began to merge some of the smaller patches from ReWind into Wine.  </p>

</section>








<section
	title="LinuxTag 2002 News"
	subject="LinuxTag 2002" 
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/06/0158.html" 
	posts="1"
	startdate="06/09/2002" 

>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>Malte Cornils wrote in with an update from LinuxTag 2002
taking place in Karlsruhe, Germany:</p>
<quote who="Malte Cornils"><p>
I'm just writing to "report" from WINE's booth during LinuxTag in
Karlsruhe, Germany. Andreas Mohr and Uwe Bonnes were the developers 
staffing the booth. Generally, there was significant interest and 
high hopes for the WINE project, requests for application support
was centered on MS Office (Word and Access mainly, also secondary MS 
apps like Visio and MS Project), Lotus Notes (but that one works
quite well already, although we didn't demo it), WYSIWIG Web editors 
(Dreamweaver, Homesite) and DTP application (very common was support 
for PageMaker, which is the predecessor to Adobe InDesign).
Illustrator and Photoshop were also common requests. The other 
notable application was Act 2000, which is some kind of Personal
Information Management Software (and it did not work :)). CAD 
software was also commonly requested, though requests were spread on 
a lot of products.
</p><p>
We tried to analyze most of the problems - I hope I can put in some 
bug reports later. We were able to solve *two* problems - Rhinoceros
3D modelling software (Andi will mail the patch later) and some 
fixes for BuildCommDCB (for some special hardware development software).
</p><p>
A personal wishlist item: I'd like to have some overview 
documentation for the tricky areas in Wine, like Interprocess 
communication and window management (how to debug this, mainly).
</p><p>
We found out that the wine debugger doesn't really work that well 
yet :-) (for me, it only worked after setting it to not using an
xterm/wconsole)
</p><p>
Marcus Meissner also stopped by and found out that most apps
(Homesite, Dreamweaver, Adobe InDesign 2.0) were using encryption to 
protect their application file, we didn't get the decryption 
working. A lot of apps would probably start working if we could
support "encrypted" binaries. I'll try to put in more detail later, 
however, you can download their trial applications and see for 
yourself :-)
</p><p>
Another area of consternation was installer support, however, most 
InstallShield-based installers worked with a native stdole32.tlb
(maybe a message to the user that (s)he needs this would be a good 
idea while we can't generate the typelib file ourselves, or is there 
some rewind stuff we could use?).
</p><p>
About games: we showed Half-life, Diablo 2, Starcraft and Grim 
Fandango, we used winex for that, though. Reaction to the
proprietary extensions of TransGaming (and sometimes CodeWeavers) 
were varied. It was a bit sad that most non-game applications each 
had some flaws (the WordArt bug for Office, dibengine problems for
MS IE, the non-working compiler backend for Visual Studio (could be 
a problem with the specific computer) and well... there weren't many 
more apps we could show because most didn't start up :))



</p><p>
Links to trial applications:
(those I mentioned above)
<ul><li>InDesign 1.5: ?</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.adobe.com/support/downloads/main.html">InDesign 2.0</a> 
        (PageMaker would also be interesting, get it from the same URL)</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.adobe.com/support/downloads/main.html">Illustrator 10</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://www.act.com/products/50/freetrial/index.cfm">Act 2000</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://www.syntrillium.com/download/download.html?1">CoolEdit 2000</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://www.macromedia.com/software/homesite/trial/">Homesite</a>
        (note: registering should not be necessary, click on "continue w/o login")</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.macromedia.com/software/trial_download/">Dreamweaver</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://download.mcneel.com/rhino/2.0/eval/default.asp">Rhinoceros 3D</a>
        (this one works great with Andi's patch!)</li>
</ul>


</p><p>
(and those that were rarely or just once mentioned, and not 
mentioned above)
<ul><li><a href="http://www.gsn.de/download/default.asp">Gandke &amp; Schubert EAR and GS-Verein</a></li>
    <li>Lemmings Revolution</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.mindjet.de/download/download.php?produkt=mm2002std-g">Mindmap</a>
        (with registration)</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.q-das.de/homepage_e/produkt%FCbersicht_e.htm">Q-Stat</a>
        (no free download. contacting them via mail requesting a demo per 
         snail mail should work)</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.xara.com/downloads/xarax/">Xara X</a></li>
</ul>

</p><p>
Photos: We made few. I hope Andi will mail an URL with them to 
wine-devel later.
</p><p>
(I hope I can post some debug logs later and put some entries in the 
bug tracking system. No firm promises though, but you can always try
most apps yourself)
</p></quote>
</section>








<section
	title="Installing Internet Explorer"
	subject="Problems running IE with latest release"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/06/0200.html"
	posts="6"
	startdate="06/11/2002"
	enddate="02/12/2002"
>
<topic>Documentation</topic>
<p>Con Hennessy was running into problems installing
Internet Explorer 4.  Won Kyu Park replied with a
detailed description of setting up IE 5.01 without a
Windows partition.  His directions for setting it up:
</p>
<quote who="Won Kyu Park"><p>
<ol>
<li> make a fake_windows in the <code>$HOME/.wine</code><br />
   <ul><a href="http://chem.skku.ac.kr/~wkpark/kle/wine/dotwine/make_dotwine">
   http://chem.skku.ac.kr/~wkpark/kle/wine/dotwine/make_dotwine</a></ul></li>

<li> install some ttf fonts(<code>$ wine NEWFNT32.exe;wine corfnt32.exe</code>)<br />
<ul><code>
  wget ftp://ftp.microsoft.com/developr/drg/TrueType/NEWFNT32.EXE<br />
  wget ftp://ftp.microsoft.com/developr/drg/TrueType/corfnt32.exe</code></ul></li>

<li> install dcom98.exe(<code>$ wine dcom98.exe</code>)<br />
  <ul><code>
  wget http://download.microsoft.com/msdownload/dcom/98/x86/en/dcom98.exe</code></ul></li>

<li> install ie5setup.exe (<code>$ wine ie5setup.exe</code>)
  <ul><code>
  wget http://download.microsoft.com/download/ie501sp2/Install/5.01_SP2/WIN98/EN-US/ie5setup.exe
  </code></ul></li>
<li> delete <code>.wine/fake_windows/Windows/WinInit.ini</code> (?)
   see Wininit.ini and you can find some instructions...</li>
<li> run explorer.exe with following config;
  (explorer.exe!! not iexplore.exe, you may copy it from some windows boxs)
  i think.. when explorer.exe executed.. some registry entries are created which
 iexplore.exe need.
<ul><code>
[AppDefaults\\explorer.exe\\x11drv]<br />
"Managed"="N"<br />
"Desktop"="800x600"<br /><br /><br />

[AppDefaults\\explorer.exe\\DllOverrides]<br />
;;<br />
"gdi32" = "builtin"<br />
"kernel32" = "builtin"<br />
;;"shell" = "native"<br />
;;"shell32" = "native"<br />
;;"commctl" = "native"<br />
;;"comctl32" = "native"<br />
"shell" = "builtin"<br />
"shell32" = "builtin"<br />
"commctl" = "builtin"<br />
"comctl32" = "builtin"<br />
;<br />
"imm" = "builtin"<br />
;"ntdll" = "native"<br />
"shdocvw" = "native"<br />
"shlwapi" = "native"<br />
"wininet" = "native"<br />
"*" = "native, builtin"</code></ul>
 </li>

<li>run iexplore.exe !!<br /><br />
<ul><code>
[AppDefaults\\iexplore.exe\\DllOverrides]<br />
;;<br />
"gdi32" = "builtin"<br />
"kernel32" = "builtin"<br />
;;"shell" = "native"<br />
;;"shell32" = "native"<br />
;;"commctl" = "native"<br />
;;"comctl32" = "native"<br />
"shell" = "builtin"<br />
"shell32" = "builtin"<br />
"commctl" = "builtin"<br />
"comctl32" = "builtin"<br />
"imm" = "builtin"<br />
;"ntdll" = "native"<br />
"shdocvw" = "native"<br />
"shlwapi" = "native"<br />
"wininet" = "native"<br />
"*" = "native, builtin"</code></ul>

</li></ol></p>

<p>
this is my screenshot.<br />

<ul><li>
( <a href="http://chem.skku.ac.kr/~wkpark/screenshot/2002_06_12_215103_shot.png">
  with "Windows"="win95"</a> )</li>
<li>
( <a href="http://chem.skku.ac.kr/~wkpark/screenshot/2002_06_12_230527_shot.png">
  with "Windows"="win98"</a> )</li></ul></p>
</quote>



<p>A lot of people were happy with the instructions, but Won
warned that it may only be useful for developers since it
can't be used as a browser.  Con wrote back and reported he
had problems getting the installation program to run.  He
also mentioned that the proper URL to download IE from
is: <a href="http://download.microsoft.com/download">http://download.microsoft.com/download</a></p>

</section>











<section 	
	title="Supporting Windows Links in the Kernel"
 	subject="Linux patch for supporting shortcuts and symlinks on VFAT"
 	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/06/0176.html"
 	posts="6"
 	startdate="06/11/2002">
<topic>Integration</topic>

<p>Patrik Stridvall requested comments about a patch thathit the linux-kernel mailing list.  
The patch allowed the kernel to parse .lnk files on VFAT partitions and treat the file as 
a symbolic link.   Patrik wondered,

<quote who="Patrik Stridvall"> It seem that at least 
some people are against it inclusion so I wonder whether we should support inclusion of 
the patch or not. I'm personally a little doubtful that it is a good idea...
</quote></p>

<p>Francois Gouget thought it was a bad idea too.  He felt the proper place to implement 
this was at the application level - Wine, KDE, GNOME, etc.  He also listed some reasons
why it would be hard to work with this in the kernel:</p>
<quote who="Francois Gouget"><p>
<ul> <li> it would prevent us from reading the information in the '.lnk'
  file... at least for 'supported' '.lnk' files</li> 
 <li> it's not entirely clear to me what they do with unsupported '.lnk'
  files. Are they just dead symlinks or can one read their contents? In
  the first case Wine is SOL again, and in the latter case we'll have to
  play games to know which kind we got.</li> 
 <li> it was suggested to implement a hack to let Wine access the '.lnk'
  data. Why implement a hack which is going to be Linux specific when
  doing nothing works just fine and on any Unix system?</li> 
 <li> making it a default option does not help Wine at all. Then we have to
  keep telling users that they have to modify their fstab if they want
  Wine to work.</li></ul></p>

</quote>
</section>





<section
  title="Preliminary BiDi Patch"
  subject="Extremely preliminary BiDi patch"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/06/0223.html"
  posts="1"
  startdate="06/12/2002"
>
<topic>Internationalization</topic>
<p>Shachar Shemesh posted an "extremely preliminary BiDi patch"
and asked for comments on lots of questions he has:</p>
<quote who="Shachar Shemesh"><p>

  Attached is an extremely preliminary BiDi patch. Here are the things 
this patch contains, and the points I would love to hear the list's 
comments about. This patch is under the LGPL only, at this stage.
</p><p>
Changes:
<ul>
    <li> Fixed the heb.nls file so that LANG=he_IL will be accepted</li>
    <li> Implemented a skeleton for GetFontLanguageInfo.
          <li> I have filled in the skeleton where I knew what to fill it
            with. I would guess that a lot of stuff is still missing.</li>
          <li> I would apretiate input on the aprorpiatness of using
            GetTextCharsetInfo as the source of information.</li>
          <li> I have removed the FIXME, but a lot of stuff is still
            unimplemented. I didn't quite know what to put there instead.</li>
    </li>
    <li> GetCharacterPlacementW - This is certanly one of the more
      overloaded functions in the Win32 set (Select object comes to mind
      as a competitor, and this one has way more execution flows
      through it). So far, as far as I could tell, only the flow that
      matched Latin fonts was implemented. I have added some (very
      basic) reordering. I would like to hear your comments about the
      following points:
          <li> I followed the autodocumentation instructions. Is this at
            all still supported or required?</li>
          <li> The algorithm I used is far from a good one. It still
            doesn't support right to left paragraphs, neutral boundary
            characters, and a bunch of other necessary stuff. All it
            does, at the moment, is make sure consecutive runs of one
            direction are, more or less, readable.</li>
          <li> I have added a fastpath option when no work is necassary.
            When all that is supported is reordering, this may make
            sense. However, I am somewhat worried that when kerning,
            ligation, glyphing etc. are added, the fastpath will be
            meaningless. Opinions?</li>
    </li>
    <li> ExtTextOutW
          <li> I am calling GetFontLanguageInfo for each and every
            ExtTextOutW (which is a focus point for all Text rendering
            functions). What performance implications will that have?
            Don't forget that what I pay for in asking whether
            reordering is necessary, I get back in not calling
            GetCharacterPlacementW, and in not allocating a buffer. Then
            again, some Unicode fonts will suffer both allocation and no
            reordering.</li>
          <li> I am calling the backend text printing function in two
            flows. One is using the allocated buffer used for
            GetCharacterPlacementW, and the other is the original (no
            point in allocating a buffer if no processing was done).
            Should I work hard to merge the two calls?</li>
          <li> I am assuming that the backend driver will not perform any
            reordering. I am not sure how correct that assumption is
            under, say, KDE3 (Hetz?).</li>
    </li></ul></p>
</quote>

<p>In a related email Shachar asked for help getting Hebrew characters
translated correctly in X.  Dmitry Timoshkov suggested changing the
<code>LC_CTYPE</code> variable.  Shachar posted to another list and
found part of his problem was not having the proper locales installed.
His solution ended up being pretty simple,
<quote who="Shachar Shemesh">
 All I had to do (I am using Debian) is 'apt-get install locales', and 
 selecting the he_IL locale (not necessarily as default). Other distros 
 will likely have somewhat different instructions.</quote>
One suggestion for RedHat users is to reinstall the glibc-common 
package since RedHat has been known for deleting unused locales after
installation.</p>


</section>



</kc>

