<?xml version="1.0" ?> 
<kc>
<title>Wine Traffic</title> 
<author>Eric Pouech and Brian Vincent</author> 
<issue num="88" date="03/26/2001" /> 
<intro>
 <p>
   This is the 88th release of the Wine's kernel cousin
   publication. It's main goal is to distribute widely what's
   going on around Wine (the Un*x  windows emulator).
 </p>
</intro>
<stats posts="52" size="169" contrib="22" multiples="9" lastweek="7">
  <person posts="13" size="37" who="Alexandre Julliard" /> 
  <person posts="5" size="18" who="James Hatheway" /> 
  <person posts="4" size="12" who="Andreas Mohr" /> 
  <person posts="4" size="12" who="Dmitry Timoshkov" /> 
  <person posts="3" size="9" who="Ulrich Weigand" /> 
  <person posts="3" size="8" who="Jeremy White" /> 
  <person posts="3" size="7" who="Lawson Whitney" /> 
  <person posts="2" size="6" who="Ian Pilcher" /> 
  <person posts="2" size="18" who="Francois Gouget" /> 
</stats>

<section 
	title="Ports to OS/390 and Sparc Machines" 
	subject="Port to OS/390 mainframe USS?"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/03/0127.html" 
	posts="7"
	startdate="03/21/2001"
	enddate="03/29/2001"
>
<topic>Ports</topic>
<p>
James Robinson asked whether there will 
<quote who="Jame Robinson">be a port of WINE to OS/390 mainframe USS?
LINUX runs fine under USS, so it would seem that WINE should run there
as well. Has anyone done this yet?</quote>
</p><p>
Ulrich Weigand answered:</p>
 <quote who="Ulrich Weigand"><p>
To clear up a possible misunderstanding first: Linux for S/390 does
*not* run under USS or under OS/390.
</p><p>
OS/390 is (one of) the standard operating system(s) used on S/390
mainframes. One component of OS/390, the Unix System Services (USS),
provides an environment that allows to run certain Unix
applications. However, USS is not itself an operating system, just an
ABI layer on top of OS/390 (somewhat similar to the POSIX subsystem of 
Windows NT).
</p><p>
Linux for S/390, on the other hand, is a true port of the Linux
operating system to the S/390 hardware. It runs directly on the S/390
platform, *instead* of OS/390 or any other mainframe operating system.
</p><p>
This has the effect that while USS is much more integrated into the
OS/390 environment, Linux on S/390 is much more similar to 'real' Unix
platforms. Porting Unix or Linux applications to USS is often
non-trivial (e.g. gcc does not run on USS at all), while porting to
Linux on S/390 is most of the time just a recompile.
</p><p>
What I want to say by that is that a port of Wine to *USS* seems
rather unlikely, given the difficulties I mentioned. However, a port
to *Linux* on S/390 should really be possible, and some time ago I
already did a proof-of-concept implementation.
</p><p>
Of course, a port of Wine to any non-Intel hardware means just a port
of the Wine *library* at the moment, as Wine does not contain an Intel
processor emulator and cannot run Windows/Intel binaries on non-Intel
hardware.</p>
</quote><p>

Under the same subject of porting Wine, Jutta Wrag asked about Sparc
support. Ulrich also answered:</p> 
<quote who="Ulrich Weigand"><p>I did send my
fixes to Alexandre; I think the current release should build on Sparc
(unless it has been broken again in the meantime -- I haven't tried
for some time).
</p><p>
In any case, that is a port to Sparc32; Sparc64 is another issue
completely (and probably much more difficult)...</p></quote>

</section>






<section 
	title="Removal of Commandline Options" 
	subject="Re: wine/ dlls/x11drv/x11drv_main.c documentation/ ..."
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/03/0147.html" 
	posts="9"
	startdate="03/23/2001"
	enddate="03/24/2001"
>
<topic></topic>
<p>
Alexandre Julliard committed a patch of his which heavily modified
some command line options:</p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p>
<ul>
	<li>the <tt>--synchronous option</tt> is now only available from the
~/.wine config file</li>
	<li>The <tt>--desktop</tt>, <tt>--display</tt> and 
	<tt>--language</tt> command-line options have been removed</li>
</ul>
</p></quote>
<p>
An astonished Andreas Mohr asked, <quote who="Andreas Mohr">Why would you
consider <tt>--desktop</tt> to be "obsolete" ?</quote>
</p><p>
Alexandre explained it was the start of a larger modification (to move 
towards 1.0), which would involve removing almost all command line
options. Alexandre explained a bit his motivations: </p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p>
Because with these command-line options kernel32 must know about and
export information specific to x11drv.
</p><p>
Also there's a larger issue of mechanism vs. policy; if we want to be
able to use the same set of Wine libraries for multiple usage (wine
loader, Winelib apps, mp3 players loading Windows dlls, etc.) we need
to move all policy decisions to the higher layers. We cannot have
kernel32 enforce a specific command-line usage, since this doesn't
apply in all cases.
</p><p>
For another instance of the same issue, see the discussion about the
deferred debug trace a couple of weeks ago: we need the Wine libraries
to provide the *mechanism* to display tracing and other information,
but the *policy* of when and how to switch tracing on or off must be
moved to higher layers (like the debugger) instead of hardcoding a
magic key sequence in user32.</p></quote> <p>(see 
<a href="wwn/87">issue #87</a> for the details.)
</p><p>
Alexandre explained also that another patch would allow those 
options to be changed (like <tt>--managed</tt>, <tt>--desktop</tt>...) 
in the config file, and also on a per application basis 
(see <a href="wwn/83">issue #83</a> 
for more details).</p><p>

Lots of developpers felt unconfortable with the trends taken by this
patch, and requested that the command line options to be still
available. 
</p><p>
One potential solution would be to run Wine from a script which would
support such command line options and set the configuration files
accordingly. 
</p>
</section>





<section 
	title="WineX on SourceForge" 
	subject="TransGaming &amp; SourceForge"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/03/0170.html" 
	posts="1"
	startdate="03/26/2001"
>
<topic>TransGaming</topic>
<quote who="Gavriel State"><p>
Just wanted to let everyone know that the TransGaming DirectX development is now
being hosted at SourceForge.  You can get updates from our live CVS tree, discuss
DirectX specific issues on the 'WineX-devel' mailing list, etc.  The SourceForge
project page is at:
  <ul><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/winex">
  http://sourceforge.net/project/winex</a></ul></p><p>

The CVSROOT for CVS is:
<ul>
 <tt>:pserver:anonymous_at_cvs.winex.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/winex</tt></ul></p><p>

We're doing WineHQ merge-ins every week or two, so things should stay relatively
up to date.  
</p><p>
Currently, we're undertaking a rearchitecture of the Direct3D work, along the
lines of the DDraw HAL work we've been contributing to the WineHQ tree.  Basically,
we're separating the glX code into the x11drv for device independence.  We're also
redoing the front end interfaces to start supporting D3D APIs both older and newer
than D3D 7.  
</p><p>
On the OpenGL front, we've done some work on the visual management code that 
solves some problems we were seeing where you couldn't get a double-buffered
visual on some cards without using -desktop mode.  I should be posting a patch
for this back to wine-patches very soon.  There are still some kinks to be worked
out...
</p></quote>
</section>
</kc>
