<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.theshell.com/~vinn">Brian Vincent</author>
<issue num="327" date="03/30/2007" />
<intro> <p>This is the 327th issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to attend a LUG meeting for the first time in five years and meet folks with a lot more + signs in their geek codes. It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="360" size="698" contrib="91" multiples="48" lastweek="46">

<person posts="28" size="72" who="speeddymon at gmail.com (Tom Spear)" />
<person posts="28" size="27" who="dank at kegel.com (Dan Kegel)" />
<person posts="24" size="21" who="hverbeet at gmail.com (H. Verbeet)" />
<person posts="33" size="93" who="stefandoesinger at gmx.at (Stefan D&#246;singer)" />
<person posts="17" size="19" who="julliard at winehq.org (Alexandre Julliard)" />
<person posts="16" size="22" who="dmitry at codeweavers.com (Dmitry Timoshkov)" />
<person posts="15" size="31" who="vit.hrachovy at sandbox.cz (Vit Hrachovy)" />
<person posts="12" size="39" who="kai.blin at gmail.com (Kai Blin)" />
<person posts="9" size="18" who="truiken at gmail.com (James Hawkins)" />
<person posts="9" size="14" who="jan.wine at zerebecki.de (Jan Zerebecki)" />
<person posts="9" size="12" who="rob at codeweavers.com (Robert Shearman)" />
<person posts="7" size="11" who="kermos at somrek.net (Stephan Rose)" />
<person posts="7" size="6" who="flexo at holycrap.org (Felix Nawothnig)" />
<person posts="6" size="34" who="kingofallhearts999 at gmail.com (Bryan Haskins)" />
<person posts="6" size="29" who="billmedland at shaw.ca (Bill Medland)" />
<person posts="6" size="9" who="scott at open-vote.org (Scott Ritchie)" />
<person posts="6" size="6" who="juan_lang at yahoo.com (Juan Lang)" />
<person posts="6" size="5" who="paul.vriens.wine at gmail.com (Paul Vriens)" />
<person posts="5" size="6" who="twickline at gmail.com (Tom Wickline)" />
<person posts="5" size="5" who="alex at thehandofagony.com (Alexander Nicolaysen Sornes" />
<person posts="4" size="13" who="wine-devel at kievinfo.com (Vitaliy Margolen)" />
<person posts="4" size="9" who="thestig at google.com (Lei Zhang)" />
<person posts="4" size="3" who="kde at 3danim.de (Markus)" />
<person posts="3" size="4" who="eric.pouech at wanadoo.fr (Eric Pouech)" />
<person posts="3" size="3" who="c-d.hailfinger.devel.2006 at gmx.net (Carl-Daniel Hailfinger)" />
<person posts="3" size="3" who="infyquest at gmail.com (Vijay Kiran Kamuju)" />
<person posts="3" size="2" who="winehacker at gmail.com (Steven Edwards)" />
<person posts="3" size="2" who="mikolaj at zalewski.pl (=?UTF-8?B?TWlrb8WCYWogWmFsZXdza2k=?=)" />
<person posts="3" size="2" who="us at edmeades.me.uk (Ann &amp; Jason Edmeades)" />
<person posts="3" size="1" who="hans at it.vu.nl (Hans Leidekker)" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="alex.pigna at inventati.org (Alessandro Pignotti)" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="ml at mathrick.org (Maciej Katafiasz)" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="sirnuke at gmail.com (Bryan DeGrendel)" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="devurandom at gmx.net (Dennis Schridde)" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="xixsimplicityxix at gmail.com (John Smith)" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="r.kalbermatter at hccnet.nl (Rolf Kalbermatter)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="philcostin at hotmail.com (Phil Costin)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="bugzilla at tut.by (Andrew O. Shadoura)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="ivg231 at gmail.com (Ivan Gyurdiev)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="fpga at pacbell.net (Duane Clark)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="jnewman at codeweavers.com (Jeremy Newman)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="Alexander.Farber at nokia.com" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="giles at gilesfreeserv.com (Giles Cameron)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="wine.dev at web.de (Detlef Riekenberg)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="timschmidt at gmail.com (Tim Schmidt)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="dank06 at kegel.com (Dan Kegel)" />
<person posts="1" size="29" who="ehoover at mines.edu (Erich Hoover)" />
<person posts="1" size="6" who="email at mathrick.org (Maciej Katafiasz)" />
<person posts="1" size="6" who="thunder.m at czela.net (Mirek)" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="dennisschridde at web.de (Dennis Schridde)" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="frick at sc-networks.de (Christoph Frick)" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="m.b.lankhorst at gmail.com (Maarten Lankhorst)" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="carlfongheiser at gmail.com (Carl Fongheiser)" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="jwhite at winehq.org (Jeremy White)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="vanoudt at gmail.com (Nicholas van Rheede van Oudtshoorn)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="marceloshima at gmail.com (Marcelo Boveto Shima)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="stonerc at gmail.com (Cye Stoner)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="ben at atomnet.co.uk (Ben Hodgetts (Enverex))" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="the3dfxdude at gmail.com (Jesse Allen)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="huw at codeweavers.com (Huw Davies)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="joris_huizer at yahoo.com (Joris Huizer)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="marcus at jet.franken.de (Marcus Meissner)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="kuba at mareimbrium.org (Kuba Ober)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="jacek at codeweavers.com (Jacek Caban)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="jim at pagesmiths.com (Jim White)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="contributions at petzi-net.de (Axel Petzold)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="us at edmeades.me.uk (Jason Edmeades)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="andrey.turkin at gmail.com (Andrey Turkin)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="arab at szluug.org (Wojciech 'arab' Arabczyk)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="jmayer at loplof.de (Joerg Mayer)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="l_bratch at yahoo.co.uk (Luke Bratch)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="der.fabe at gmx.net (Fabian Bieler)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="dbialac at yahoo.com (Dave Bialac)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="artur.szymiec at gmail.com (Artur Szymiec)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="fgouget at free.fr (Francois Gouget)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="frank.richter at gmail.com (Frank Richter)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="Andrew.Talbot at talbotville.com (Andrew Talbot)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="saulius2 at ar.fi.lt (Saulius Krasuckas)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="lich at math.spbu.ru (Kirill K. Smirnov)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="jwhite at codeweavers.com (Jeremy White)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="richard at sheugh.com (richard)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="wjsqudtlr at gmail.com (Byeong-Sik Jeon)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="ead1234 at hotmail.com (EA Durbin)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="mikolaj at zalewski.pl (=?ISO-8859-2?Q?Miko=B3aj_Zalewski?=)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="dimi at lattica.com (Dimi Paun)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="remco47 at yahoo.com (Remco)" />

</stats>
<section 
title="News: CrossOver &amp; Linspire"
subject="News"
archive="http://cvs.winehq.org/cvsweb/wine/ANNOUNCE?rev=1.138&amp;content-type=text/x-cvsweb-markup"
posts="1"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>Wine 0.9.34 hath fallen from the sky.  Changes noted:</p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p><ul>
<li> Support for Xcursor.</li>
<li> A range of fixes for various installers.</li>
<li> New builtin xcopy tool.</li>
<li> The usual assortment of Direct3D fixes.</li></ul></p></quote>

<p>More detail can be found in the 
<a href="http://cvs.winehq.org/cvsweb/wine/ChangeLog?rev=1.134&amp;content-type=text/x-cvsweb-markup">ChangeLog</a>.
Download, run, <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org">report bugs</a>.
</p>

<p>CodeWeavers has sold their CrossOver Office product through Linspire's
CNR (formerly known as Click 'N Run) store for quite a while.  They announced 
this week that version 6.0 is 
<a href="http://www.sys-con.com/read/351006.htm">now available</a> through 
that outlet:</p>
<quote who="Sys-Con Media"><p>
Linspire, Inc. developer of the Linspire commercial and Freespire community 
desktop Linux operating systems and developer of CNR, a one-click digital 
software delivery service for desktop Linux applications, libraries and 
packages, and CodeWeavers, Inc., the leading Windows-to-Linux software 
developer, today announced the release and support of CrossOver Linux 6.0 for 
CNR. This marks the latest CodeWeavers upgrade for the market leading product 
that allows the running of native Windows applications within a desktop Linux 
operating system. Incorporating substantially improved support for many popular 
games, including World of Warcraft, Half-Life 2 and Counterstrike, CrossOver 
Linux 6.0 now offers CNR users more flexibility than ever to run the Windows 
applications they need. CrossOver Linux 6.0 is immediately available via 
digital download using the CNR one-click download and installation software 
delivery system at: 
<a href="http://www.linspire.com/crossoveroffice">
http://www.linspire.com/crossoveroffice</a></p></quote>

<p>In the news, WindowsIT Pro (the magazine every Linux administrator is
glad they don't have to read) had an article about 
<a href="http://www.windowsitpro.com/Articles/ArticleID/95628/95628.html"><i>Linux on the Desktop</i></a>
where they mentioned Wine:</p>
<quote who="WindowsIT Pro"><p>


Anyway, with Wine (the Windows emulator) installed on Linux I found that I can 
run my favorite Windows-based email client and RSS application, so I don't 
have to switch to some other Linux-based varieties. Not that I'd use them very 
much anyway - my primary desktop system is Windows-based, but it's nice to have 
them available if the need arises. </p></quote>

</section>
<section 
title="Road to 1.0"
subject="Road to 1.0"
archive="http://www.winehq.com/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-March/055147.html"
posts="34"
>
<topic>Project Management</topic>
<p>Wine 1.0... oh yes... some day it will happen.  The bold even go so far as to
<a href="http://www.winehq.com/wwn/296#Beta:%20How%20We%20Got%20Here">make 
predictions</a> of when it will happen.  Discussion of criteria for 1.0
came up this week, which is usually the sure sign there's a jinx that will
put off 1.0 by another year.  Dave Bialac started it innocently enough:</p>
<quote who="Dave Bialac"><p>
I've been following the list for about a year now, just reading and
learning.  Through this process, I've come to wonder about the
following question -- what should be the goal for Wine 1.0?  I know a
lot of development is focused around getting one particular
application or another to work, especially from the folks over at
CodeWeavers, but with version numbers approaching 1.0, should there
not be a set goal of functionality?  My personal thought is that Wine
should head in the direction of 100% compatibility with a particular
version of Windows.  Anything that ran on that version should run on
Wine 1.0 with no problems.  Any thoughts?</p></quote>


<p>Rob Shearman quickly pointed out that 100% compatibility isn't realistic,
however specific applications could be targeted.  That led Dan Kegel to
comment:</p>
<quote who="Dan Kegel"><p>

Yes indeed.  And the only reason I haven't jumped up
and posted a proposed list of applications to support
for 1.0 is that real app testing is gobs of work, more
than we have resources for.
</p><p>
The tests at <a href="http://cxtest.org">http://cxtest.org</a> could be an 
important part of the equation.</p><p>

FWIW, a couple of us have been puttering away on a scheme
to make writing application regression testers easier.
No promises, though.</p></quote>

<p>Tom Wickline summarized some discussion we had last fall at WineConf:</p>
<quote who="Tom Wickline"><p>
I see Wine 1.0 as a set of features that AJ has decided upon, once the
feature set is in the tree then a feature freeze will go onto effect...
Then one to six months of only bug fixes. Then ouila! 1.0 is born.

At the last Conf if memory serves me correctly there was mention of a
feature freeze happening sometime early this year. And I would only
guess to say the release notes after the freeze would read "X" amount
of bugs were fixed in this release, as no new features would be
implemented.
</p></quote>

<p>Alexandre confirmed that process was the plan and what it might take
to get there:</p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p>

That's still the plan, yes. I'm mostly waiting for the games support
to stabilize; the other main areas, office apps and installers, both
seem in good enough shape at this point.  I'm also hoping we can make
some progress on the x11drv factorisation before the freeze, so that
we don't need to change the interface too much to add the quartz
driver later on, we'll see how that goes. And if we delay it a bit
more maybe we can slip in Safedisc support too...
</p><p>

Clearly there will always be "office" apps that don't work, the
question for the code freeze is whether we have all the pieces we
need; I don't think there's a major feature at this point that would
prevent typical office apps from working. Now, whether a specific app
works is a different question, but as long as it only requires bug
fixes it can be addressed after the freeze, or on the stable branch
after 1.0.
</p></quote>

<p>Wait... did you catch that?  It's rather succinct, but that right 
there is the roadmap for Wine for the next year.  </p><p>
There was a bit more discussion with several people commenting on the
area of Wine they'd like to see improved before stamping a 1.0 on the tree.
</p>
</section>
<section 
title="DirectX To-Do List"
subject="http://www.winehq.com/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-March/055390.html"
archive="Game road to 1.0" 
posts="13"
>
<topic>DirectX</topic>
<p>The crazy talk continues!</p>

<p>Stefan D&#246;singer brought up the topic of what should be sorted
out in the DirectX world in order for Wine to get a "1.0" stamp.  
Right now that's probably the area in Wine most in
flux, so it's something to think about.  Stefan started the conversation
with a to-do list of sorts:</p>
<quote who="Stefan D&#246;singer"><p>
In another thread Alexandre has mentioned to wait for game stuff to stabilize
before the 1.0 freeze. I think it's time for another brainstorm of what
features are still missing which we want in 1.0. The DirectX Todo has a long
list but it tends to be useless to me. And I see that it can use some more
cleanup ( /me blames Tom-W for not nagging me enough :-) ) It also sounds like
AJ takes games as an excuse to delay the freeze for the display driver
cleanup, and I was tempted to take the display driver cleanup as an excuse to
get more dx stuff in.
</p><p>
So which of the following things do we want for 1.0?
</p><p>
Direct3D:<ul>
<li> Some SM 3.0 features are still missing. Instancing is now in, vertex
textures and some other stuff still missing. Not widely used among games yet.</li>

<li> Multithreading. OpenGL part done (except of 3 patches which I'll NOT send for
now (see note below), but needs synchronisation. Will take a lot of time.</li>

<li> OpenGL ddraw. Render target locking improvements, multithreading.</li>

<li> Many games do not run yet, problems on Mac OS X drivers and fglrx. For the D3D
part I see that as bugfixes which can happen after the freeze as far as I
understand things.</li>

<li> Direct3D10. Will see if someone applies for my SoC proposal.</li>
</ul></p>
<p><i>note:</i> The patches that do the context selection. I won't send them because with
my testing patches people started hunting phantom bugs which were the result
of missing synchronisation.

</p><p>
DirectSound: Maarten plans to work on that for SoC I think. Freezing now would
make that difficult. Would mean to delay the freeze until September / October
most at least. I'd personally really appreciate dsound and alsa working
better in 1.0.
</p><p>
OpenGL: I don't really know of the windowed opengl state, and the wined3d ->
wgl move. Still planned?
</p><p>
DirectPlay: Kai works on the protocol, but I think he doesn't plan to
implement it anytime soon. It seems the current idea is to improve our
networking libs to get native dplay working.
</p></quote>

<p>Alessandro Pignotti then mentioned that he was planning on working on
DirectPlay.  </p><p>

Henri Verbeet gave his thoughts regarding Stefan's list:</p>
<quote who="Henri Verbeet"><p>
While nice to have, I don't think d3d10 or some of the more advanced
SM 3.0 features should block 1.0. You already know my opinion on
broken drivers.
</p><p>
Things that aren't there, but IMO should be:<ul>
<li> Make GLSL default</li>
<li> Make FBOs default</li>
<li> Support HDR / float textures</li></ul></p><p>

There are various cleanups that should be done as well (eg, getting
rid of FVFs completely), but I'm not sure if those should block 1.0 or
not.
</p></quote>

<p>Roderick Colenbrander filled in the details regarding Stefan's original
mention of moving WineD3D to WGL:</p>
<quote who="Roderick Colenbrander"><p>

OpenGL needs to get proper windowed opengl rendering support. The best route to that seems to be by using opengl child windows. There's a patch for it but it needs cleanups and then AJ needs to accept it ...
</p><p>
After that the rest of OpenGL can be cleaned up. For instance the pixelformat limitation can be lifted and because of that various things can be done in a proper way. Second multisampling will be possible as well.
</p><p>
After OpenGL is stable, WineD3D can be moved over to WGL.</p></quote>


</section>
<section 
title="0.9.33 Benchmarks"
subject="Wine Benchmarks and CAPS"
archive="http://www.winehq.com/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-March/055483.html"
posts="6"
>
<topic>Testing</topic>
<p>Curious how Wine is doing against the competition?  Ever wonder what
Wine's multitexture 3D fill rate capacity is?  Tom Wickline finished
a set of benchmarks against Wine 0.9.33 that include answers to those 
questions.  Tom's post:</p>
<quote who="Tom Wickline"><p>


I have the 0.9.33 page done, and you may notice that Wine regressed in
a couple of the tests. When looking at these scores you will need to
take into account the actual visual quality . The scores were somewhat
high in past tests because everything wasn't being rendered, while that
makes for a nice score the visual wasn't on par with that of Windows.
</p><p>
As of 0.9.33 the visual quality is very close to that of Windows, so
in a test like 3DMark2001SE we not only got drastically improved visual
quality, we also have a 50% improvement in performance! And 3DMark 03
has a nice showing out of the gate as well.
</p><p>
Why no OpenGL test?
</p><p>
I plan to wait for a resolution to a couple outstanding OpenGL bugs,
and then run the tests again. I also plan to dramatically increase the
screen resolution in the next update, GL-Excess in the past was run at
only 640x480x16; in the future all tests will be run at a resolution of
1024x768x32 or greater.
</p><p>
If all goes well in a couple months there should be another update
with OpenGL tests and 3DMark 05/06 results. If 3DMark 2000, 2001SE or
2003 should drastically change i'll also update them as well at that
time.
</p><p>
I also updated the CAPS page with 0.9.33 and 1.0.9755.
</p><p>
0.9.33 results:
<ul><a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMark-0.9.33">
http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMark-0.9.33</a></ul>
</p><p>
Past results:
<ul><a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMarks">
http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMarks</a></ul>
</p><p>
CAPS results:
<ul><a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/DirectX-Caps">
http://wiki.winehq.org/DirectX-Caps</a></ul>
</p><p>
Some screen shots of past test results.... You may want to look at
them ASAP if you are interested in them, I plan to ask Dimi to rm -rf the
page in a couple weeks to save the HD space on the wiki server, this
way I can start a new "In Progress" page and not feel guilty about
uploading all the shots :D
</p><p>
<ul><a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMark-0.9.6">
http://wiki.winehq.org/BenchMark-0.9.6</a></ul>
</p></quote>

<p>The benchmarks highlight something interesting about Wine's
performance.  Since Wine sits on top of the Linux kernel and uses
the underlying device drivers and such, there's an opportunity for
better performance than Windows itself in some areas.  For example,
disk reads/writes and memory access usually perform well with Wine.
In reality, there's still a lot of areas of Wine that could use
a lot of optimization and things don't always work as well.  Yet
these tests prove the potential is there.</p>
</section>
<section 
title="Testing &amp; Older Windows Versions"
subject="Excluding a Windows version from the tests"
archive="http://www.winehq.com/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-March/055511.html"
posts="8"
>
<topic>Testing</topic>
<p>Paul Vriens asked:</p>
<quote who="Paul Vriens"><p>
yesterday a patch of mine was committed to test more profile stuff from 
kernel32. When I have a look now at test.winehq.org I see that some test(s) 
crash on win98 but not on others.
</p><p>
Although I could use a if(0) construction (as is done in several other tests), 
I'm wondering if we should just not run specific tests on specific Windows 
versions. It's a shame that one OS version blocks the running of several other 
tests.
</p><p>
I have no idea yet how to achieve this without building in GetVersion style 
things, as logic and return values don't always make a good distinction.
</p></quote>


<p>Alexandre suggested it's time to just stop worrying about Win9x
failures.  The platform has reached the end of its usable life (some
would say it had reached the end of its usable life the day it was
released, but that's another matter.)  Paul summarized a course of
action for tests:</p>
<quote who="Paul Vriens"><p>

So if we only have crashes on win9x we don't care. If we can avoid 
crashes/failures on win9x (by skip or other means) we don't run them on win9x. 
And if they crash on something higher than win9x we disable them totally.
</p></quote>

<p>Alexandre thought that was fine but explained why explicit version
checking is bad:</p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p>
Sure; the thing we want to avoid is version checks in tests, because
then things don't get tested on Wine when the version is changed. But
as long as win98 is detected by its missing features then skipping
things is fine.
</p></quote>


</section>
<section 
title="Wine's Coverity Contact"
subject="Wine's official Coverity contact(s)"
archive="http://www.winehq.com/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-March/055416.html"
posts="3"
>
<topic>Project Management</topic>
<p>Paul Vriens announced he volunteered himself to be the Wine contact
for Coverity scanning:</p>
<quote who="Paul Vriens"><p>


A few days ago I've received an email from Mikolaj Zalewski requesting an
account for Coverity !?
</p><p>
I know that in the past some of us dealt with Coverity already. I had a look at
the new website and apparently things changed with respect to creating (and
approving) new accounts. (Before the new website came alive I think just sending
an email got you an account). I must say it's not clear to me how the process
currently works but sending an email to scan-admin@coverity.com should do the
trick. The approval then has to be done by the main contact(s).
</p><p>
The next step will be that the main contact(s) will have some kind of
administration rights to add/change/delete(?) accounts (at least that's how I
understood it).
</p><p>

I'm currently in contact with one of the Coverity guys and volunteered to be one
of the main contacts. I had a look through the list of current users and all of
them look valid to me.
</p><p>

I think it will be good to have one or two more main contacts. So anyone
volunteering? There will hardly be any work involved (I hope). Mainly dealing
with approving new accounts and communicating things back to the Wine community.
</p></quote>

<p>Jan Zerebecki volunteered to be a contact as well.</p>


</section></kc>
