<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Kernel Cousin Wine</title>

<author email="vinn@theshell.com">Brian Vincent</author>

<issue num="117" date="03/08/2002" />

<intro>
<p>
This is the 117th release of the Wine's kernel cousin publication. Its main 
goal is to distribute widely what's going on around Wine (the Un*x Windows 
emulator). </p>

</intro>



<stats posts="355" size="1279" contrib="83" multiples="44" lastweek="60">

<person posts="38" size="157" who="Patrik Stridvall &lt;ps@leissner.se&gt;" />
<person posts="38" size="155" who="Guido Draheim &lt;guidod-2002-@gmx.de&gt;" />
<person posts="36" size="95" who="Brett Glass &lt;brett@lariat.org&gt;" />
<person posts="29" size="78" who="Andriy Palamarchuk &lt;apa3a@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="14" size="57" who="Sean C. Farley &lt;scf@farley.org&gt;" />
<person posts="13" size="32" who="Alexandre Julliard &lt;julliard@winehq.org&gt;" />
<person posts="10" size="43" who="Roger Fujii &lt;rmf@lookhere.com&gt;" />
<person posts="10" size="26" who="lawson_whitney@juno.com" />
<person posts="10" size="25" who="Andreas Mohr &lt;andi@rhlx01.fht-esslingen.de&gt;" />
<person posts="9" size="22" who="Sylvain Petreolle &lt;spetreolle@yahoo.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="8" size="29" who="Dmitry Timoshkov &lt;dmitry@baikal.ru&gt;" />
<person posts="9" size="79" who="list@vmn.com.br" />
<person posts="6" size="14" who="Francois Gouget &lt;fgouget@free.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="21" who="Anthony Taylor &lt;tony@paperdove.org&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="14" who="Michael Robertson &lt;michael@lindows.com&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="13" who="Gerhard W. Gruber &lt;sparhawk@gmx.at&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="11" who="Eric Pouech &lt;eric.pouech@wanadoo.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="18" who="David Elliott &lt;dfe@tgwbd.org&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="13" who="mehmet yasar &lt;myasar@free.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="9" who="Marcus Meissner &lt;marcus@jet.franken.de&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="8" who="Steven Edwards &lt;steven_ed4153@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="4" size="8" who="Jeremy Newman &lt;jnewman@codeweavers.com&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="14" who="Guy L. Albertelli &lt;galberte@neo.lrun.com&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="10" who="Michael Cardenas &lt;michaelc@lindows.com&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Mike McCormack  &lt;mike_mccormack@start.com.au&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Ove Kaaven &lt;ovehk@ping.uio.no&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="77" who="Michael Cardenas &lt;michaelc@lindows.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="14" who="Paul Millar &lt;paulm@astro.gla.ac.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="9" who="Boris Buegling &lt;boris@icculus.org&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="Ignasi Villagrasa &lt;gri@netcom.es&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Geoff Thorpe &lt;geoffthorpe@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="James A Sutherland &lt;james@sutherland.net&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Steven Edwards &lt;Steven_Ed4153@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Uwe Bonnes &lt;bon@elektron.ikp.physik.tu-darmstadt.de&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="John Alvord &lt;jalvo@mbay.net&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Eric Pouech &lt;eric.pouech@voila.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Roland &lt;roland@netquant.com.br&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="chaitu6u &lt;chaitu6u@indiatimes.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Dimitrie O. Paun &lt;dpaun@rogers.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="J.Brown (Ender/Amigo) &lt;ender@enderboi.com&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="Dimitrie O. Paun &lt;dimi@cs.toronto.edu&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="David.Goodenough@DGA.co.uk" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="J. Christopher Pereira &lt;kripper@users.sourceforge.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="24" who="leanne &lt;leanne@thizlinux.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="7" who="jonathan &lt;jonathan@corvu.com.au&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="6" who="Jeremy Shaw &lt;jeremy@lindows.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Martyn Ranyard &lt;ranyardm@lineone.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Anthony Fok &lt;anthony@thizlinux.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Michael Stefaniuc &lt;mstefani@redhat.de&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Steve Langasek &lt;vorlon@dodds.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Zdenek Kabelac &lt;kabi@informatics.muni.cz&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Dave Hawkes &lt;daveh-wine@cadlink.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Joerg Mayer &lt;jmayer@loplof.de&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Sander van Leeuwen &lt;sandervl@xs4all.nl&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="michael cardenas &lt;michaelc@lindows.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Keith Matthews &lt;keith_m@sweeney.demon.co.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Tony lambregts &lt;lambregt@telusplanet.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="law@redhat.com" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Nick Temple &lt;ntemple@tgl.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="David Laight &lt;david@l8s.co.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Jeremy White &lt;jwhite@codeweavers.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Rick Romero &lt;rick@valeoinc.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Jakob Eriksson &lt;jakob@vmlinux.org&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Rein Klazes &lt;rklazes@xs4all.nl&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="&lt;winedev@admdev.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Philipp Wollermann &lt;phil_wo@gmx.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dan Kegel &lt;dank@kegel.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="daveh-wine@cadlink.com" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Shane Shields &lt;locutusenterprises@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Duane Clark &lt;dclark@akamail.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Ken Reneris &lt;ken@reneris.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="jasonp &lt;jasonp1@cox.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="lists@giantblob.com" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Drew Ogle &lt;og1@umbc.edu&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Christian Jires &lt;ds98chji@thn.htu.se&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="lists &lt;lists@giantblob.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="robert w hall &lt;bobh@n-cantrell.demon.co.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Lionel Ulmer &lt;lionel.ulmer@free.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Hetz Ben Hamo &lt;hetz@kde.org&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Per Wigren &lt;wigren@home.se&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="ricardo &lt;r00tzz@yahoo.co.uk&gt;" />

</stats>


<section
  title="CrossOver 1.1.0"
  subject="News"
  topic1="News"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-cvs/2002/02/0147.html"
  posts="2"
  startdate="02/25/2002"
  enddate="03/08/2002"
>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codeweavers.com">CodeWeavers</a> released 
version 1.1.0 of their CrossOver Plugin.  The additions
are fairly impressive.  From the release notes:
<ul>
	<li>support for multi-user environments</li>
	<li>support for Windows Media Player streams</li>
	<li>Truetype font support</li>
	<li>new plugin support including iPIX, Macromedia
	    Authorware, and Trillian</li>
</ul>

You can download a copy from their website for $24.95 or get it on
CD for $35.95.</p>

<p>
Also this week was the release of wn20020228.  This may be the last BSD 
licensed version of Wine released, and certainly the last from Alexandre.
The changes include:
<ul>
	<li> Client-side font rendering using Xrender.</li>
	<li> Local server COM support.</li>
	<li> Many DrawText improvements.</li>
	<li> A ton of fixes for better MS Office support.</li>
	<li> Preliminary support for C unit tests.</li>
	<li> Lots of bug fixes.</li>
</ul></p>

</section>


<section
  title="Wine Licensing (con't)"
  subject="Conclusions"
  topic1="Licensing"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-license/2002/03/0029.html"
  posts="37"
  startdate="03/04/2002"
  enddate="03/05/2002"
>
<p>
The biggest news of the week is again the licensing debate.  Alexandre
began bringing the discussion to a close:</p>

<quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
<p>
 I would like to close this discussion now and proceed with the license
 change. Here's a summary of the various points that have been
 discussed and the conclusions I draw from them.
</p><p>
 <u>License choice</u>
</p><p>
 The possible copyleft licenses that have been discussed are:
<ul>
  <li> LGPL</li>
  <li> MPL (Mozilla license)</li>
  <li> MPL/LGPL/GPL multi-license</li>
  <li> LGPL with modifications to section 2d</li>
  <li> xGPL with time delay on code release</li>
</ul>
</p><p>
 As already mentioned, the LGPL is the favorite of the majority of
 people who voted in favor of copyleft. I have not seen arguments
 compelling enough to make one of the alternatives a clearly better
 choice, especially since they all have some other drawbacks that have
 been discussed. So the logical choice is to go with the LGPL.
</p><p>
 <u>LGPL ambiguities</u>
</p><p>
 Some people have remarked that in some cases it's not exactly clear
 what the LGPL allows or doesn't allow. I think this is inevitable
 given the nature of what the license tries to achieve, and any other
 license with the same goals would have the same problems. I'm
 confident that this is not going to be a real problem in practice;
 border cases can be resolved simply by discussion among the
 contributors (on this mailing list for instance). The existence of
 binary drivers for the Linux kernel plainly demonstrates that these
 things can be worked out.
</p><p>
 <u>Header files</u>
</p><p>
 Some people have suggested using a different license for header
 files. I don't think this is really necessary, given that the LGPL
 doesn't impose extra restrictions on headers compared to the current
 license (LGPL headers don't influence the license of the code compiled
 with them, and you cannot really distribute headers without source
 anyway). And having everything under the same license makes things a
 lot simpler.
</p><p>
 <u>WineCorp</u>
</p><p>
 The suggestion of assigning copyrights to an organization to allow
 relicensing under different terms seems to be generally disliked. It
 may still be useful to have a non-profit org to manage other aspects
 of the project, but since setting this up is a non-trivial amount of
 work I'm not going to pursue it at this point.
</p><p>
 I'll shortly be making a general announcement of the change, and I'll
 then begin switching the CVS tree license to LGPL. If some people feel
 the need to maintain an X11-licensed fork (though I hope this won't
 prove necessary), they should use the 20020228 release as the starting
 point for that tree.
</p></quote>

<p>Alexandre went on to list the plan for implementing the change:</p>
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard"><p><ul>
 <li> add COPYING.LIB file containing LGPL version 2.1</li>
 <li> change LICENSE file to refer to COPYING.LIB</li>
 <li> add notice/exception in spec compiler output</li>
 <li> (probably) add notice in all source files following FSF guidelines</li>
 <li> make new release announcing the change</li>
 <li> start accepting LGPL patches</li>
</ul></p></quote>

<p>Michael Robertson invited everyone to talk about it at the planned
Wine conference next week, 
<quote who="Michael Robertson">
 Since there's two group dinners planned, these might be a good time for the 
 licensing discussion to take place. Unless one of the attendees decides to 
 use their presentation time to cover this topic in a more formal arena. 
</quote></p>


<p>Needless to say, there were some people who were unhappy with
the license change.  But the decision seems to have been made.  A lot 
of specific problems will be worked
out over time.  The 
<a href="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-cvs/2002/03/0000.html">first CVS commit</a>
for March contained the change. In response, Gavriel State from TransGaming voiced 
his concerns:</p>

<quote who="Gavriel State"><p>
I noted today with disappointment (but not surprise) the switchover in WineHQ 
CVS to LGPL.  While this is going to have significant repercussions on the way 
that TransGaming works on Wine, I will leave our views on that subject to some
other time.
</p><p>
I do have two specific legal issues to raise - I would have raised them earlier
this week, but I have not had the time to respond until today.  
</p><p>
1) Switching to the LGPL in the manner done today violates the previous Wine 
license, which states:
 <blockquote>
 ... 
 The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
 all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
 </blockquote>
</p><p>
The new LICENSE file includes the 'above copyright notice', but not 'this 
permission notice'.  The LGPL can certainly be applied to newly written 
code, but I believe that it is improper to apply it to all of the existing
code in the tree.  
</p><p>
The AFPLed TransGaming WineX tree deals with this issue by: 
<ul>
 <li> Renaming the original LICENSE file to LICENSE.WineHQ</li>
 <li> Replacing the LICENSE file with the AFPL</li>
 <li> Identifying all modified files with TransGaming's copyright notice</li>
 <li> Prefacing the new LICENSE file with the following:
 <blockquote>
   Source code and other software components explicitly identified as 
   Copyright TransGaming Technologies Inc. is covered by the license
   below.  Other source code and software components are covered by the
   Wine license, found in the LICENSE.winehq file.
 </blockquote></li>
</ul>
</p><p>
Something similar should suffice for the WineHQ LGPL switch.  Explicitly
identifying files that now include LGPLed components is probably a good
thing regardless.
</p><p>
2) Header files.  Under the same logic that allows the Wine project to 
build header files compatible with Microsoft's own, the appropriateness
of applying the LGPL to the header files is suspect. From a post of mine 
to wine-devel about a year ago:
</p><p>
 Copyright law does not protect idea, just the expression of them. 
 Several court decisions have been rendered which suggest that the 
 'purely functional' elements of a computer program are not copyrightable. 
 There are several cases that explicitly deal with the issue of copyright 
 and header files. The most relevant one for Wine development is 
 probably the 1992 decision in Sega v. Accolade, where Accolade reverse 
 engineered the headers for Sega's ROM libraries in order to develop 
 games compatible with Sega's hardware without paying Sega's royalties. 
 ( 
  <a href="http://www.eff.org/pub/Legal/Cases/sega_v_accolade_977f2d1510_decision.html">
  http://www.eff.org/pub/Legal/Cases/sega_v_accolade_977f2d1510_decision.html</a> ) 
 The court in that case said: 
</p><p>
 <blockquote>
  Computer programs pose unique problems for the application of the 
  "idea/expression distinction" that determines the extent of copyright 
  protection. To the extent that there are many possible ways of 
  accomplishing a given task or fulfilling a particular market demand, 
  the programmer's choice of program structure and design may be highly 
  creative and idiosyncratic. However, computer programs are, in essence, 
  utilitarian articles -- articles that accomplish tasks. As such, they 
  contain many logical, structural, and visual display elements that are 
  dictated by external factors such as compatibility requirements and 
  industry demands... In some circumstances, even the exact set of 
  commands used by the programmer is deemed functional rather than 
  creative for the purposes of copyright. When specific instructions, 
  even though previously copyrighted, are the only and essential means 
  of accomplishing a given task, their later use by another will not 
  amount to infringement. 
 </blockquote>
</p><p>
The LGPL acknowledges this legal issue in section (5): 
</p><p>
 <blockquote>
  When a "work that uses the Library" uses material from a header file 
  that is part of the Library, the object code for the work may be a 
  derivative work of the Library even though the source code is not. 
  Whether this is true is especially significant if the work can be 
  linked without the Library, or if the work is itself a library. The 
  threshold for this to be true is not precisely defined by law. 
 </blockquote>
</p><p>
 Rather than be subject to this ambiguity, it may be simpler for the
 headers to fall under the previous license, since the previous
 license still needs to be there regardless.
</p></quote>

<p>Alexandre felt the method used to switch license was fine,
<quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
  It is definitely not improper, this is allowed by the sublicense case
 of the license. In that case obviously the old permission notice no
 longer applies; I'm still going to add it somewhere for documentation
 purposes, so that part of the license will be respected.
</quote>  As far as identifying files in CVS that can be used under the
old license, Alexandre explained a new tag, <quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
 From now on all files should be considered as containing LGPL
 components. I have added a "Before-LGPL" tag that allows retrieving
 previous versions when necessary. It doesn't make much sense IMO to
 try to identify specific files since the LGPL applies to whole
 libraries, not files.</quote>  He also felt header files should be under 
the same license just so moving stuff around would be easier.  </p>

<p>Gav still felt that the interpretation of the sublicense part
of the license was suspect:</p>
<quote who="Gavriel State">
<p> 
 To grant a right to 'sublicense' means that a licensee is allowed to 
 license a copyright work to someone else - the terms under which a licensee
 can sublicense are still covered by the original license, which required
 that permission notice to be included with the code.
</p><p>
 <a href="http://www.lawyers.com/lawyers-com/executable/glossary/defpage.asp?SEQNO=8275">
 http://www.lawyers.com/lawyers-com/executable/glossary/defpage.asp?SEQNO=8275</a>
</p><p>
Perhaps Eben Moglen can be helpful here.  It's a shame that he has not had
any input into this process to this point; there are a number of issues that
have been brought up that it would probably be worth discussing with him.
</p></quote>
<p>Alexandre replied, 
 <quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
  Well, it's included now. I can certainly include the text in every
  source file if you like, though it's not clear that this is necessary
  (and it wasn't done before either). The spirit of the license is 
  clearly respected since the copyright notices are still there, the
  warranty statement is practically identical in the LGPL, only the
  permission text is different obviously because the permissions under
  the new license are different. I really don't see a problem here.
 </quote></p>

 

</section>



<section
  title="X11 Fork"
  subject="The X11 Fork"
  topic1="Project Management"
  topic2="Licensing"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-license/2002/03/0093.html"
  posts="4"
  startdate="03/10/2002"
  enddate="03/10/2002"
>

Ove K&aring;ven posted the first message about using the existing Wine
code under the X11 license:
<quote who="Ove Kaaven"><p>
Since it's official that Wine has gone LGPL, it's also official that there
will be an X11-licensed fork. So far, 4 independent movers have stepped
forward, all volunteering to look after this fork; Kenneth Davis, Gerard
Patel, Eric Pouech, and me. Several others have stated their support for
it, and will contribute either directly or indirectly (by licensing their
Wine contributions under the X11 license). While we would like to move
forward with this, and request that as many Wine contributors as possible
give us permission to apply their contributions to the X11 fork, we must
first decide on a few things.
</p><p><ul>
<li> What do we call the fork.<br />
  Kenneth suggested "winem", and already created a sourceforge project
  with this name. Afterwards, Gerard suggested "Theleme" to him (from
  "Abbey of Theleme"). Then later, Eric mailed me and suggested OpenWine. 
  Others?<br /><br />
 </li>
<li> Where do we host it.<br />
  SourceForge is an option, but in the long term it would be preferable
  with a somewhat more independent place to host it.<br /><br />
 </li>
<li> Who is in charge.<br />
  While a development model where more than one person can do stuff like
  committing patches etc may be a good idea, we still ought to choose
  someone that's ultimately responsible...
  <br /><br />
  Or, would we maybe rather prefer to have a WineCorp in charge?<br /><br />
 </li>
<li> Who's in?<br />
  If you want to join the X11 fork, or just support our efforts by
  continuing to license your patches under the X11 license, let us know.
 </li></ul>
</p><p>
Anything else?
</p></quote>

<p>Joerg Mayer suggested hosting it at winehq.org, 
 <quote who="Joerg Mayer">
 I don't think there will be too many hard feelings
 in the lgpl-wine team (at least I hope so) and it looks like there will
 (hopefully) be quite a lot of cooperation between the two teams.
 </quote>
</p>

<p>Alexandre also pointed out, 
 <quote who="Alexandre Julliard">
 I guess this is obvious to everybody except Brett, but I just want to
 make it clear that any code that gets added to the X11 fork can also
 be merged into the LGPL tree. In fact, allowing this was the only
 reason for the license change from BSD-like to X11 a couple of years
 ago, which at the time everybody agreed was a good thing. If the
 contributors to the X11 fork do not want this to happen they will have
 to change to a license that explicitly prevents it.
 </quote></p>

<p>There will likely be a lot more posts on this topic, so look for this
thread to continue.</p>

</section>





<section
  title="WineHQ Moved"
  subject="WineHQ.org Move Complete"
  topic1="Project Management"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/03/0048.html"
  posts="4"
  startdate="02/28/2002"
  enddate="03/05/2002"
>
<p>On Thursday, February 28th Jeremy Newman from CodeWeavers 
announced:</p>
<quote who="Jeremy Newman"><p>
 NOTICE!! NOTICE!! NOTICE!!</p>

 <p><a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a>
 will be moving to a new home in Minnesota. We are trying
 to make this move as seamless as possible, but we can't guarantee that
 there will not be any downtime. I will post another message to the
 mailing lists when I have a more definite time of shutdown of the old
 server.</p>

 <p><a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a> 
 WILL be on-line for Web, FTP and CVS access. The area
 that could have the longest downtime is the mailing lists. </p>

 <p>Once the transfer is complete, winehq.org, winehq.org, and
 wineproject.org will be one and the same site.</p> 

 <p>If you run a mirror of winehq.org please contact me to make arrangements
 for access.</p>

 <p>Further questions can be directed my was as well.</p></quote>

<p>A few days later, on Tuesday, Jeremy announced:</p>
<quote who="Jeremy Newman"><p>
 The WineHQ.org move is complete, but not without some issues.
</p><p>
 The 1st issue is that our mailing lists (mailman) sent out a huge amount
 of email because the newsgroup gateway changed. It basically thought all
 the messages on comp.emulators.ms-windows.wine were new. Apologies go
 out to the users whose email inboxes we filled up.
</p><p>
 So in the meantime, the newsgroup gateway, and the NNTP server on
 winehq.org are offline until further notice.
</p><p>
 If you notice any other issues that I am not aware of, please let me
 know. There is a lot of things to a site that has been running as long
 as WineHQ.org has.
</p></quote>

<p>There was no reply, which is probably a good thing.</p>


</section>







<section
  title="Tasklists in Bug Tracking System"
  subject="update on bug #11 and #435, newbie questions"
  topic1="Project Management"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/03/0017.html"
  posts="2"
  startdate="03/01/2002"
  enddate="03/01/2002"
>
<p>
Jason Phillips was going through some bug lists and mentioned,
<quote who="Jason Phillips">
 I'm new to Wine development and was checking out bug #11 (from "tasklet" 
 meta-bug #406) I added some comments for it. It seems beyond the 
 scope of a beginner type bug. See bug for details.</quote></p>

<p>Francois Gouget replied:</p>
<quote who="Francois Gouget"><p>
   I moved it to a new list called FIXMEs. It is intended as an
intermediate list for fully diagnosed bugs. That's the third list but
don't worry, I intend to stop there.
<ul>
   <li> Tasklets
     <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=406">
     http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=406</a></li>
   <li> FIXMEs
     <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=455">
     http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=455</a></li>
   <li> Tasklist
     <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=395">
     http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=395</a></li>
</ul></p><p>

   Now, I really must get going on that contrib page.</p>
</quote>

<p>If you look at the section of the bug detail "Bug XXX depends on:"
you'll see a list of bugs for that category.  "Tasklets" are the easiest
ones.</p>

</section>





<section
  title="Wineconf Agenda"
  subject="Update: Agenda for wineconf 2002"
  topic1="Commercial Development"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/03/0016.html"
  posts="2"
  startdate="03/01/2002"
  enddate="03/01/2002"
>
<p>Next Friday and Saturday Lindows.com will be hosting Wineconf.  The
presentations will be video taped by <a href="http://www.lpbn.org/">lpbn.org/</a>
and a URL will be posted later.  Michael Robertson posted an updated agenda 
for next weekend:</p>
<quote who="Michael Robertson"><p>
There are 2 areas that we'll be focusing on:
</p><p>
Business issues - This will be a combination of presentation from companies 
talking about their business experience with WINE as well as talks on the 
non-technical issues facing WINE. 
</p><p>
Wine Technology - There will be some advanced topics as well as some more 
general overviews. Since (<a href="http://www.lpbn.org/">http://www.lpbn.org/</a>) 
will be on hand to shoot video 
of all the session, our goal is to have a video series that those newer to 
wine can view at anytime via the net to get up to speed. Alexandre's keynote will set 
the tone and provide a roadmap for many of the discussions. Alexandre's 
keynote will kickoff the conference. 
</p><p>
NOTE: Presentations listed below with a * designate a Friday presentation. If 
there's no asteric, then the presentation will be on Saturday. For maximum 
diversity, we will be alternating between technology presentations and 
business. There will be two technology presentations and then one on a 
business topic. Repeat. 
</p><p>
  <u>Wine Technology</u>
</p><p>
WINE Past, Present and Future [Julliard]*<br />
Supporting Drag and Drop between Wine and non-Wine windows [Weigland]*<br />
How To Make Fonts Look Great In Wine [Davies]*<br />
Package streamlining of WINE [Meissner]*<br />
DirectX [Kaaven]*<br />
IActiveScript, or how jscript.dll was reimplemented using the Mozilla
JScript engine, lots of glue, and a little bit of luck". [Hatheway]*<br />
Beyond Trial And Error, Alternative Ways To Insure Quality Code [Stridvall]<br />
A Howto For Regression Testing [Gouget]<br />
Winedoc and Automated Verification [Paun]<br />
Wine/Windows bootup handling and documentation/end user representation [Mohr]<br />
Package streamlining of WINE [Meissner]<br />
TBD [Czekalla]
</p><p>
  <u>Business Talks</u>
</p><p>
Macadamian - Making It As A Software House [Boulanger]*<br />
An Unique Commercial Application for WINE [Cadlink Technology/Hawkes]*<br />
Gaming and Beyond  [TransGaming/State]*<br />
ReactOS - Where it's at, where it's going [ReactOS/Filby]<br />
Corel, A Look Back [Xandros/Tranter]<br />
Lindows.com And WINE [Robertson]
</p></quote>



</section>





<section
  title="Quicken and TurboTax"
  subject="Thanks -- well done"
  topic1="Fixes"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/03/0040.html"
  posts="1"
  startdate="03/05/2002"
  enddate="03/05/2002"
>
<p>
Jeff Law wrote:</p>
<quote who="Jeff Law"><p>
 I've been following Wine development for the last 6 months, mostly watching
 for improvements for the 2 Windows applications I actually care about --
 Quicken and TurboTax.
</p><p>
 Quicken has been mostly usable for that entire time period; however it's
 behavior has significantly improved.  Far fewer hangs, crashes and other
 undesirable behavior.  I won't enumerate the problems y'all have fixed,
 but the user-visible progress has been great.  There's still some rough
 edges, but the improvements have been huge.
</p><p>
 TurboTax was basically unusable until recently -- but when I returned from
 a short vacation and updated my wine sources, all the show-stopping issues
 with TurboTax had been resolved.  Amazing.
</p><p>
 The one issue in both tools that I still need to check on is both
 consistently ran out of GDI space, which I've hacked around with some 
 tweaks to gdiobj.c. 
</p><p>
 There was a 3rd application I've been evaluating (RentTracker) which was
 also unusable in mid-Feb, but which appears to work flawlessly now. 
</p><p>
 I just wanted to let you know that you've made great strides recently 
 and your work is greatly appreciated.  
</p></quote>


</section>



<section
  title="Bug in OLE"
  subject="new Bug in OLE"
  topic1="Patches"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/02/0871.html"
  posts="3"
  startdate="02/27/2002"
  enddate="02/28/2002"
>
<p>Mehmet Yasar experienced a problem running Microsoft Visual
Studio 6:</p>
<quote who="Mehmet Yasar"><p>
 Microsoft Visual Studio 6 is crashing when opening an existing projet,
 with current CVS version of Wine (Wine20020122 was OK).
</p><p>
 Comparing both, I have found the change that triggers the crash.
 It is function StgOpenStorage in OLE32/storage32.c, line 5595 :
 <ul><code>
   hr = StorageImpl_Construct(<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        newStorage,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        hFile,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        pwcsName,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        NULL,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        grfMode,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;        TRUE,<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp; 	-      FALSE);<br />
   &nbsp;&nbsp;		+      !(Fad.nFileSizeHigh || Fad.nFileSizeLow) /* FALSE */ );
</code> </ul>
TRACE shows that Fad.nFileSizeHigh = Fad.nFileSizeLow = 0;
</p><p>
As you can see in TRACE the crash occurs in StorageImpl_WriteBigBloc.
I suppose Wine is trying to write to a readonly opened file ?
(because file is opened with GENERIC_READ)
</p><p>
I hope this will help finding a fix.
</p></quote>

<p>Mike McCormack replied:</p>
<quote who="Mike McCormack"><p>
 I created the problematic change in question.
</p><p>
 Without the change, when StgOpenStorage is called with an existing
 zero length file as the filename, it fails because it succeeded in
 opening the file but expects it to have valid content...
</p><p>
 Unfortunately, the change was merged incorrectly from the big CW
 patch. (the Fad structure is not initiaized)
</p><p> 
 Could you try 
  <a href="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/02/att-0885/01-storage.diff">
  this patch</a> instead please?
</p></quote>

<p>Mehmet reported the patch worked.</p>

</section>



<section
  title="More COM Work"
  subject="Out of process COM objects &amp; InstallShield v6"
  topic1="Fixes"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2002/02/0800.html"
  posts="3"
  startdate="02/24/2002"
  enddate="02/26/2002"
>
<p>
Sander van Leeuwen wondered:</p>
<quote who="Sander van Leeuwen">
<p>
 What's the current state of OOP COM objects in Wine?
 I've noticed a lot of related changes, but have yet to find an InstallShield 6
 installer that works. (I did copy the stdole*.tlb files to the windows &amp; system directory)
</p><p>
Before I start debugging this, I'd like to know if it is supposed to work at all.
</p></quote>

<p>Marcus Meissner wrote back, 
<quote who="Marcus Meissner">
 I am not sure when and how this NdrDllRegisterProxy appeared, but I am
 experiencing the same problem.</quote>  Ove K&aring;ven posted a small
patch showing why it works for TransGaming.  He felt the patch was 
pretty bad and would almost certainly be rejected.  The patch worked
for Marcus and he felt it should be included.  </p>

<p>And related to this, Marcus mentioned debugging wasn't very useful,
<quote who="Marcus Meissner">
 Oh and debugging might not really help, support for proxies registered with
 NdrDllRegisterProxy needs to get implemented. </quote></p>

<p>Ove replied, <quote who="Ove Kaaven">
 I've been working on this as part of my COM restructure. I've implemented
 NdrDllRegisterProxy and large pieces of rpcrt4's marshalling framework. I'd
 like to release it to WineHQ, but Gav still wants something in exchange.
 (If we can't get money, we'll consider releasing it if a Wine developer
 agrees to work on stuff that may be useful for us, like an ALSA driver,
 and/or a Wine kernel module to speed up synchronization primitives (like
 mutexes), or maybe more DirectShow work, or something of the kind.)
</quote></p>

</section>




</kc>
