<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.theshell.com/~vinn">Brian Vincent</author>
<issue num="226" date="06/11/2004" />
<intro> <p>This is the 226th issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to grill. It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="85" size="371" contrib="41" multiples="15" lastweek="16">

<person posts="12" size="34" who="Mike Hearn" />
<person posts="8" size="23" who="Robert Shearman" />
<person posts="7" size="27" who="Eric Pouech" />
<person posts="6" size="63" who="Luca Capello" />
<person posts="4" size="19" who="Shachar Shemesh" />
<person posts="4" size="14" who="Chris Morgan" />
<person posts="3" size="20" who="Erich Hoover" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="Robert Reif" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="Paul Millar" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="Joshua Walker" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="hatky" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Fabian Cenedese" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Robert Lunnon" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Saulius Krasuckas" />
<person posts="1" size="35" who="Twickline" />
<person posts="1" size="16" who="Fabian Franz" />
<person posts="1" size="9" who="Raphael" />
<person posts="1" size="7" who="Raghavan Gurumurthy" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="mguyard" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Patrick Spinler" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Raghavan Gurumurthy" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Shachar Shemesh" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Uwe Bonnes" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="David Lee Lambert" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dmitry Timoshkov" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dimitrie O. Paun" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Jonathan Fosburgh" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="P. Christeas" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Izak Burger" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Maurizio Monge" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Paul Davis" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Bill Medland" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Mike McCormack" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="(markus.amsler)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Francois Gouget" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Alexandre Julliard" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="James Courtier-Dutton" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who=" (Morten Welinder)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="John Birrell" />

</stats>
<section 
	title="News: The Linux Show Broadcast, eWeek Review" 
	subject="News"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/00.html" 
	posts="2"
	startdate="06/05/2004"
	enddate="06/11/2004"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>Jeremy White appeared on 
<a href="http://www.thelinuxshow.com/">The Linux Show</a> this
week.  The show is archived at <a href="http://www.thelinuxshow.com/archives.shtml">http://www.thelinuxshow.com/archives.shtml</a>
Along with that, eWeek <a href="http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1602124,00.asp">
reviewed</a> CrossOver Office 3.0.  It's postive, though it
lacks much in the way of detail (I get the distinct impression
the author installed it and only ran it once.)</p>

<p>Other than that, there's not much going on.  Alexandre is on vacation
and everyone else seems to be taking a break accordingly.</p>

</section>
<section 
	title="Kernel Bug Creating Zombies" 
	subject="Zombie processes"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/0145.html" 
	posts="7"
	startdate="06/07/2004"
	enddate="06/09/2004"
>
<p>Shachar Shemesh asked for help tracking down what
appears to be a kernel bug:</p>
<quote who="Shachar Shemesh"><p>
Mike M told me on IRC that this matter has come up before, but I have 
not been able to find it in the archives. It seems Wine has been 
generating lots of zombie processes when it's not 100% cleanly killed. I 
have also seen the system hold a socket created from a wine process in 
"ESTABLISHED" state, when no process is registered as the socket's owner.
</p><p>
According to Alexandre according to Mike, this is a kernel bug. Well, it 
most certainly is. Theoretically, there is nothing a user space process 
can do to cause zombies to stay around after their parent has exit, or 
keep sockets open after their controlling process has quit. As wine is a 
user space only process, this must be a kernel bug. No way around it.
</p><p>
However, it happened to me both on RedHat 9 with 2.4.something (NPTL 
back ported), with both RH9's original kernel, and their most up to date 
one. It also happened on Debian Sid's almost-vanilla kernel 2.6.6. It 
happened with LD_ASSUME_KERNEL=2.4.1 making wine choose the standard 
threading mode, as well as without, choosing nptl. The zombies are 
sometimes called wine-pthread/wine-kthread, and sometimes 
wine-preloader. In short, I think this is a long standing Linux kernel 
bug, and Linus helps those who help themselves. I will also not be 
surprised if it was triggered by a wine bug.
</p><p>
So the question is this. Is there anyone on this list who knows how to 
submit this as a question to lkml? 
</p></quote>

<p>Shachar mentioned he had a tainted kernel due to Nvidia drivers.
Rob Shearman confirmed he experienced the same thing though,
<quote who="Rob Shearman">
 I've experienced the same thing on a perfectly clean kernel (I think
 2.6.5-mm1), but I assumed it was because we were messing around with
 signals. If I can reproduce the problem I will report it, although Mike
 McCormack seems to have had quite a bit of contact already with the kernel
 folks</quote></p>

<p>Mike McCormack wrote in with a few more details,
<quote who="Mike McCormack">
 The problem seems to be a kernel bug.  It's been round since 2.6.0... in 
 my experience it only seems to happen when you terminate a wine process 
 using <tt>^C</tt> or when the program crashes tries to start the debugger, fails, 
 then you press <tt>^C</tt></quote></p>

<p>From there more reports trickled in with the same issue.
Kernels with this problem included an untainted  2.6.5 and an
"untainted" RedHat 2.4.20-8.  Shachar thought that offered a
bit of insight into the problem,
<quote who="Shachar Shemesh">
 if I am guessing correctly, this problem has something to do 
 with NPTL, which means it was only there in the 2.4 kernel to begin with 
 because of a RedHat patch. However, as the problem DOES happen on 
 vanilla 2.6 kernel, this will not be a problem to reconstruct.
</quote></p>

</section>
<section 
	title="Killing Wine" 
	subject="Warning about ultra-confusing thing"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/0146.html" 
	posts="1"
	startdate="06/07/2004"
>
<topic>Fixes</topic>
<p>Killing a Wine process may not be as straight forward as you'd 
think.  Mike Hearn gave a pointer to anyone experiencing this problem:</p>
<quote who="Mike Hearn"><p>

Sometimes it is convenient to do a "<tt>killall -9 wine-pthread</tt>" to kill Wine
for whatever reason. This no longer works:<ul><code>

$ ps ax | grep wine-pthread | grep -v grep
10425 pts/4    S      0:00 /opt/wine/bin/wine-pthread notepad.exe<br /><br />

$ killall wine-pthread<br />
wine-pthread: no process killed<br />
$ killall wine-preloader<br />
$</code></ul></p><p>

Huh? WTF is going on here? Well, it seems that "ps" and "killall" look at
different places to get the process name, so despite the fact that it
appears as wine-pthread in the process list, you must use the name
wine-preloader in order to send it signals from the command line.
</p><p>
There are reasons for this, which will hopefully become clear when I
submit my docs on the Wine init process. For now, you have been warned.
</p></quote>


</section>


<section 
	title="Detecting Wine" 
	subject="How to determine if an application is running in Wine environment?"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/0173.html" 
	posts="3"
	startdate="06/09/2004"
>
<topic>Fixes</topic>
<p>
This topic comes up from time to time, although it's
been a while since we've seen it.  Raghavan Gurumurthy
asked,
<quote who="Raghavan Gurumurthy">
 If i want to do some special handling inside my Windows 
 executable when running in Wine environment, what is the 
 best way to do this?</quote></p>

<p>Mike Hearn gave the preferred answer,
<quote who="Mike Hearn">
 if you are trying to work around a Wine bug a better
 approach is just to fix it.</quote></p>

<p>Bill Medland had the other answer - how to actually
detect a Wine environment,
 <quote who="Bill Medland">Unless things have changed, 
 I think the normal suggestion is to look for the 
 <tt>HKLM/Software/Wine</tt> registry key</quote></p>

<p>Josh Walker thought working around deficiencies might
lead to problems later if Wine needed to change the registry
layout for compatibility reasons.  Raghavan explained that
their intentions were simply to ensure they were able to
provide the best compatibility possible on Linux:</p> 
<quote who="Raghavan Gurumurthy">
<p>The purpose of my question was to make sure that wherever we are doing
changes to the product code to work-around limitations in Wine, we are doing
so only when running on Wine. And, before you (or anyone else) send further
flame mail, note that we are submitting fixes to Wine as and when we run
into them and have a solution. </p>

<p>We are not trying to limit the product in anyway on Linux - if any, we are
trying to make sure that the end-user experience for our product when
running on Linux is as painless and seamless as possible.</p>
</quote>

<p>Chris Morgan thought it might be a good opportunity to identify areas
of Wine that need work,
<quote who="Chris Morgan">
I'd be curious as to what kinds of things you 
are trying to work around.  It would be interesting to see in which cases 
bugs were worked around vs. fixed and which areas were the biggest problems.
</quote></p>
</section>
<section 
	title="Winrash Update" 
	subject="Winrash update"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/0179.html" 
	posts="1"
	startdate="06/09/2004"
>
<topic>Testing</topic>
<p>Chris Morgan updated the Winrash tool used to run
Wine's test suite and asked for people to please register:</p>
<quote who="Chris Morgan"><p>
Just released a new version of winrash.  I'm sending this email because after 
asking people who are running Winrash to send an email to the list or 
myself , I didn't receive any emails.  This isn't usually a problem except 
when there is an issue with Winrash.  I get error reports that have the IDs 
people put in but no way to contact them.
</p><p>
So I added a field in the installer for a contact email.  This will be sent 
along with the clientID when an error report is generated by winrash.  
</p><p>
In case anyone is curious the web archive for the error reports is here: 
<ul><a href="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-tests-results/">
http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-tests-results/</a></ul>
</p><p>
I'd like to ask that anyone who installed winrash please run the installer 
again so they can enter a valid contact email.  If you are one of those 
people wondering why your results aren't found at 
<ul><a href="http://test.winehq.org/data/">
http://test.winehq.org/data/</a></ul> this will help both of us by letting me get a 
hold of you ;-)
</p><p>
The one change I should mention is the addition of proxy support in the 0008 
release.  There are a handful of people running behind proxies, I can tell by 
squid html in what should be the script part of the error reports.  This 
version of the client *should* fix things for you.  Thanks to Florian Steinel 
for the code change.
</p><p>
Here is the SF link to the latest client:
<ul><a href="http://osdn.dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/winrash/winrash-0008-chris-msvc.exe">
http://osdn.dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/winrash/winrash-0008-chris-msvc.exe</a></ul>
</p><p>
Thanks to anyone running the testing suite and for the feedback on winrash 
changes, I appreciate it.
</p></quote>

<p>In case you missed the original announcement about the automatic
testing facility (see 
<a href="http://www.winehq.com/wwn/224#Testing%20-%20Volunteers%20Needed">issue 
#224</a>), Winrash is a service you can run on Windows to help
validate the accuracy of Wine's tests.  So if you've got a spare PC
laying around, give it a shot.  It's bandwidth requirements are minimal -
a full Wine test suite is only about 650k.  Even if you only boot into 
Windows occasionally it can provide useful results.</p>

</section>
<section 
	title="Blizzard Updater Fix" 
	subject="Blizzard Updater Problem"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/0123.html" 
	posts="8"
	startdate="06/05/2004"
	enddate="06/08/2004"
>
<topic>Fixes</topic>
<p>Erich Hoover couldn't get the Blizzard Updater to run,
<quote who="Erich Hoover">
 I haven't been able to get the blizzard updater to run on recent 
 versions of wine (I've downloaded from CVS to make sure there isn't a 
 fix).  I'm not sure if this is something wrong with my setup or a bug 
 with wine (i recently reinstalled my system with Fedora Core 2 and am 
 no-longer running the same version of wine).  I'm executing programs 
 with "setarch i386 wine &lt;appname&gt;" but the blizzard updater seems hosed 
 (though Diablo II and Warcraft III run fine).  It appears that the 
 updater doesn't launch correctly
</quote></p>

<p>Rob Shearman asked for some more info so that he could debug
it.  Saulius Krasuckas sort of recognized the problem; it appeared
to affect a few other programs.  He  gave a bit of a background on it:</p>
<quote who="Saulius Krasuckas"><p>
 AFAICS this case may be related to already known issue [1].
</p><p>
 The bug is still present in the CVS.  If it's the same bug I urge to
 reverse this patch [2] (if compiling by yourself) or just use Wine version
 prior to the date "2004/04/19 23:02:35".  For me reversing [2] patch
 worked out fine.
<ul>
[1] <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2210">http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2210</a><br />
[2] <a href="http://cvs.winehq.org/patch.py?id=12071">http://cvs.winehq.org/patch.py?id=12071</a>
</ul></p></quote>

<p>Rob then created <a href="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2004/06/att-0135/01-dialog_init.diff__charset_">a
patch</a> and asked if it fixed the problem.  Both Saulius and Erich
reported success.</p>

</section></kc>
