<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.theshell.com/~vinn">Brian Vincent</author>
<issue num="193" date="10/24/2003" />
<intro> <p>This is the 193rd issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to be scared of ghosts and goblins. It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="228" size="668" contrib="76" multiples="38" lastweek="34">

<person posts="21" size="62" who="Dimitrie O. Paun" />
<person posts="14" size="36" who="Vincent B&#233;ron" />
<person posts="11" size="32" who="Mike Hearn" />
<person posts="11" size="30" who="Shachar Shemesh" />
<person posts="11" size="19" who="Ivan Leo Murray-Smith" />
<person posts="9" size="30" who="Szakacsits Szabolcs" />
<person posts="9" size="20" who="Alexandre Julliard" />
<person posts="8" size="33" who="Steven Edwards" />
<person posts="7" size="24" who="Gregory M. Turner" />
<person posts="7" size="18" who="Dmitry Timoshkov" />
<person posts="7" size="14" who="Tom" />
<person posts="5" size="20" who="Jan Kratochvil" />
<person posts="5" size="14" who="Ferenc Wagner" />
<person posts="5" size="13" who="Gerhard W. Gruber" />
<person posts="5" size="12" who="Fabian Cenedese" />
<person posts="4" size="11" who="Jonathan Wilson" />
<person posts="4" size="9" who="Jakob Eriksson" />
<person posts="4" size="9" who="Lionel Ulmer" />
<person posts="3" size="9" who="Sylvain Petreolle" />
<person posts="3" size="9" who="Dietrich Teickner" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Rein Klazes" />
<person posts="3" size="8" who="Rolf Kalbermatter" />
<person posts="3" size="6" who="Hans Leidekker" />
<person posts="2" size="11" who="Steven Tower" />
<person posts="2" size="9" who="Earnie Boyd" />
<person posts="2" size="9" who="Boaz Harrosh" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="Jason Filby" />
<person posts="2" size="8" who="Brian Vincent" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Thomas Mertes" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Robert Reif" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Andreas Mohr" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Rolf Kalbermatter" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Keith Matthews" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Jeremy Newman" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="Jon Griffiths" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Vitaliy Margolen" />
<person posts="2" size="4" who="Jason Edmeades" />
<person posts="1" size="7" who="Subhobroto Sinha" />
<person posts="1" size="7" who="Pavel S. Khmelinsky" />
<person posts="1" size="7" who="Robert Shearman" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Geoff Thorpe" />
<person posts="1" size="4" who="Eric Kohl" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="flyker" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Gerald Pfeifer" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Mathias Berchtold" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Julien C" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Sami Aario" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Martin Troester" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="SysAdmin" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Uwe Bonnes" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Stefan Leichter" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="John Smith" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Carlos Lozano" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dan Kegel" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Kjetil S. Matheussen" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Oleg Prokhorov" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="George Marshall" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Ralf Juengling" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Danny Smith" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Jeremy White" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Shachar" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dave Miller" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Marcus Meissner" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Huw D M Davies" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Paul Kopacz" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="(julienc)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Acke Carlsson" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Kevin DeKorte" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Maxime Bellenge" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Francois Gouget" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Daniel Marmier" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Beartooth" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="David D. Hagood" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Eric Pouech" />

</stats>
<section 
	title="News: Press Coverage" 
	subject="News"
	archive="http://www.theinquirer.net/?article=12207"
	posts="3"
	startdate="10/18/2003"
	enddate="10/24/2003"
>
<topic>News</topic>
<p>Boo!</p>
<p>Tom Wickline pointed out The Inquirer wrote a short article discussing
<a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/?article=12207">device driver 
compatibility layers.</a>  Wine was mentioned several times in the
article as well as Odin, the OS/2 Wine spinoff.  But don't let it fool
you - Wine is pretty much useless for drivers.  
</p>

<p>Slashdot posed a question - how much of a 
<a href="http://ask.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=03/10/24/2157206&amp;mode=thread&amp;tid=125&amp;tid=130&amp;tid=185&amp;tid=190&amp;tid=201">security threat</a> is Wine?
The resulting discussion was all over the place not too unlike a trainwreck
with bodies strewn about. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.codeweavers.com/">CodeWeavers</a>
 revamped their website.  A quick glance didn't show any added
features. </p>
</section>
<section 
	title="WineSetupTk Resurrected" 
	subject="winesetuptk"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2003/10/0405.html" 
	posts="20"
	startdate="10/12/2003"
	enddate="10/24/2003"
>
<topic>Configuration</topic>
<p>Last year it was decided that the future of Wine configuration would
be a Winelib app.  That project has turned into Winecfg with Mike Hearn as
the active contributor.  Winecfg remains a work in progress and there's a
lot of functionality still missing.  In the past the only graphical
configuration tool was WineSetupTk developed by CodeWeavers.  
A few weeks ago Vincent B&#233;ron
pointed out some problems with it due to a lack of maintenance.  Ivan
Leo Murray-Smith explained why it would be beneficial to have it working:</p>
<quote who="Ivan Leo Murray-Smith"><p>
Most normal people (Users) don't want to edit config files or use a shell.
That's why most people don't use linux. Winecfg isn't complete, winesetuptk will
go soon, but in the meantime it's the best way to configure wine. I get emails
all the time from people thanking me for putting winesetuptk on sourceforge,
it's had a lot of downloads, and I don't think we can remove it yet. As soon as
winecfg is ready, I'll hide winesetuptk (That won't work anyway because wine
won't read the config file). Until then, winesetuptk is the only easy way of
configuring wine, and I have no intention of telling users 
"Go and edit the config file and add this and remove that and make a system
directory inside the windows directory that's in your fake c:\ drive that the
config file has to point to..." when I can just say "Install winesetuptk, start
it, and follow the on-screen instructions". I don't see how such a good level of
usability can hurt.</p></quote>
<p>This week Ivan announced some updates had been made:</p> 
<quote who="Ivan Leo Murray-Smith"><p>
Rc1 had a bug that caused winesetuptk to crash when it looked for a real windows
drive and didn't find one.
Also, with rc2 winver is set to 98, as a lot of apps refuse to install on 95.
</p><p>
source
<a href="http://www003.portalis.it/115/download/prerelease/winesetuptk0.7rc2.tar.bz2">
http://www003.portalis.it/115/download/prerelease/winesetuptk0.7rc2.tar.bz2</a>
</p><p>
binary
<a href="http://www003.portalis.it/115/download/prerelease/winesetuptk0.7rc2.bz2">
http://www003.portalis.it/115/download/prerelease/winesetuptk0.7rc2.bz2</a>
</p></quote>

</section>
<section 
	title="RedHat 7.3 Packages" 
	subject="RH7.3 packages"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2003/10/0438.html" 
	posts="1"
	startdate="10/13/2003"
>
<topic></topic>
<p>Meant to include this last week.  Vincent B&#233;ron,
RedHat package maintainer, announced:</p>
<quote who="Vincent Beron"><p>
Some time ago somebody asked here about RedHat 7.3 Wine packages. I said
I'd do it, pending some hardware upgrade on one of my box.
</p><p>
That time has now come, and they are available on the 
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=6241">sf.net
download page</a>. Only i386 and src for now, no athlon nor i686.
</p></quote>

<p>Checking up on this, Vincent has updated the page to include last
week's Wine-20031016 release as well as add packages for i686.
</p>


</section>
<section 
	title="User Forums (Maybe) Resurrected" 
	subject="Proposal to resolve the issue of the broken wine-users gateway"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2003/10/0706.html" 
	posts="7"
	startdate="10/23/2003"
>
<topic>Project Management</topic>
<p>Speaking of dying slow deaths, Wine's user community has been
a bit neglected since the Usenet-mailing list gateway died.  Jeremy
White tossed out some ideas for improving that line of communication:</p>
<quote who="Jeremy White"><p>

Say, Just chatting on IRC today, and ShadowHawk pointed out
that a host of other sites (Franks corner, etc) have sprung up
almost entirely because there are no user based forums
on winehq.org.
</p><p>
This is, in part, due to the fact that the gateway between
the newsgroup and wine-users is busted.  And it is that way,
because the gateway we were using is a dead project, and Jer
hasn't been able to wrestle it back into working 
(and doesn't really want to).
</p><p>
Further, I think it may be time to recognize that cool looking
forums are what users expect; that mailing lists and newsgroups
are really becoming the 'old' way of doing things.
</p><p>
Further, there is a PHP based forum system that Jer would be
happy to put up on winehq.org.
</p><p>
This would neatly side step the whole problem and perhaps provide
a nice upgrade for winehq.org.
</p><p>
What do others think?</p></quote>

<p>Dimi Paun replied first,
<quote who="Dimitrie Paun">
I for one don't think highly of other forms of forums, but this
is not the issue. I think we should fix the gateway, and also
provide one of these fancy forums. If people like them, all
power to them. In fact, I think we should implement the Slashcode
(or something similar) for the News box. Would be very nice to
see the reactions of people to important news that happen in
the community, but are not *that* important to start a thread
about on wine-devel.</quote></p>

<p>Jeremy Newman, the website maintainer, felt the Usenet gateway was a 
dead issue and would remain with other rotting corpses that have fallen
by the wayside.  He explained a bit about the forum he had in mind,
<quote who="Jeremy Newman">

The software I mentioned to Jer that we could implement is 
Phorum. <a href="http://phorum.org/">http://phorum.org</a> I've 
played with it in the past,
and integrating it into the current site is dead easy.</quote></p>
<p>
Concerning the ability to comment on a news story, Jeremy thought
of a simple way to do that,
<quote who="Jeremy Newman"> 
Exactly, whenever a news post, or new WWN, or Wine version is posted, I
can start a new thread in the forum, and link to that thread from the
news article on the front page. Easy, and effective.

</quote></p>

<p>Dan Kegel didn't like the idea at all because it wasn't easily
searchable by Google.</p>
</section></kc>
