<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Kernel Cousin Wine</title>

<author email="brianv@ski-copper.com">Brian Vincent</author>

<issue num="105" date="10/03/2001" />

<intro>

<p>This is the 105th release of the Wine's kernel cousin publication. Its
main goal is to distribute widely what's going on around Wine (the Un*x 
Windows emulator).</p>

<p>Alexandre kicked out release 20011004 this week.  The announcement lists
the following changes:</p>
<p><ul><li>Beginnings of shared window handles.</li>
	<li>Much improved typelib support.</li>
	<li>Tons of new code in quartz dll (ActiveMovie)</li>
	<li>Lots of bug fixes.</li>
</ul></p>


<p>This week in the news we have 
<a href="http://searchwindowsmanageability.techtarget.com/originalContent/0,289142,sid33_gci772798,00.html">
an interview</a> with Jim Graham, the
CTO of CodeWeavers.  Jim wraps up the interview with:</p>
<p><quote who="Jim Graham">
A CTO of a large organization with a thousand desktops can buy 
one copy of Red Hat Linux, for example, and install it on all 
of those desktops without violating any license agreements. With 
that, you've got the ability to maintain those from one central 
location and work with servers and communicate with any other 
desktop (Macintosh, Apple, or Windows) all from the same environment. 
We might see a larger utilization of Linux in the workplace, but 
I don't believe we're going to get all of the applications over 
there immediately. There's going to be a demand to provide both 
until there's more application software in the Linux market. 
Tools like this are going to provide that bridge.</quote></p>

</intro>

<stats posts="74" size="272" contrib="32" multiples="13" lastweek="16">

<person posts="8" size="89" who="Ove Kaaven &lt;ovehk@ping.uio.no&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="21" who="Uwe Bonnes &lt;bon@elektron.ikp.physik.tu-darmstadt.de&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="19" who="Dmitry Timoshkov &lt;dmitry@baikal.ru&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="18" who="Andreas Mohr &lt;a.mohr@mailto.de&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="10" who="Daniel Walker &lt;diwalker@earthlink.net&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="9" who="Alexandre Julliard &lt;julliard@winehq.org&gt;" />
<person posts="5" size="8" who="Bill Medland &lt;medbi01_1@accpac.com&gt;" />
<person posts="6" size="16" who="Eric Pouech &lt;eric.pouech@wanadoo.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="3" size="11" who="lawson_whitney@juno.com" />
<person posts="3" size="9" who="Nog &lt;Nog@sdf.lonestar.org&gt;" />
<person posts="2" size="6" who="Francois Gouget &lt;fgouget@free.fr&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Lucien LaCroix &lt;lacroixlucien@hotmail.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="5" who="Nikolas Zimmermann &lt;wildfox@kde.org&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Huw D M Davies &lt;h.davies1@physics.ox.ac.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="David Hammerton &lt;david@transgaming.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="Nerijus Baliunas &lt;nerijus@users.sourceforge.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Ian D. Stewart &lt;idstewart@compuvative.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Aric Stewart &lt;aric@codeweavers.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Michael Stefaniuc &lt;mstefani@redhat.de&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dominik Strasser &lt;dominik.strasser@mchp.siemens.de&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Dan Kegel &lt;dank@kegel.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Robert Lunnon &lt;bob@yarrabee.net.au&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Guilherme Kunz &lt;guiok@ig.com.br&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Luke Stras &lt;stras@ecf.toronto.edu&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="Mrugan Bhorkar &lt;mruganb@yahoo.co.uk&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Charles Wyble &lt;jackshck@yahoo.com&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Marcus Meissner &lt;Marcus.Meissner@caldera.de&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Gerard Patel &lt;gerard.patel@nerim.net&gt;" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Daniel Sabo &lt;DanielSabo@hotmail.com&gt;" />

</stats>



 

<section
  title="Debugging MFC Programs"
  subject="can't debug mfc program"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/10/0003.html"
  posts="4"
  startdate="10/02/2001"
  enddate="10/02/2001"
>

<p>Guilherme Kunz was having a problem getting a program to run after compiling it
with winelib.  He was going through the following steps:</p>
<quote who="Guilherme Kunz"><p>
	I am trying compile a mfc program with winelib. 
	</p><p>
	Well, i compiled the part of mfc which i need for use the program without 
	erros or unresolved functions and compiled the mfc program with the 
	libmfc.so without errors or unresolved functions, but when i ran the mfc 
	program happened "Segmentation Fault". 
	</p><p>
	I tried use gdb and winedbg but i can't run these debuggers, with gdb 
	happened "Segmentation Fault" with or without breakpoints in the 
	beginning of the source and winedbg write only the first line in the 
	window and go out. 
</p></quote>
<p>Francois Gouget wanted to know what kernel and compiler version was being used.
Eric Pouech just wanted to know what the one line of output was.  And Aric 
Stewart thought that the problem was more widespread:</p>
<quote who="Aric Stewart"><p>
	This appears to not just be mfc programs.. recently I have been unable
	to use gdb on any wine program with either the 2.4.0 or 2.4.9 kernels.
	</p><p>
	same problems, i get a seg fault when loading libntdll.so
</p></quote>
 


</section>  








<section
  title="Submitting Patches"
  subject="CVS, diffs, and a newbie (me)"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/10/0020.html"
  posts="3"
  startdate="10/04/2001"
  enddate="10/04/2001"
>

<p>Daniel Sabo wrote in wondering, <quote who="Daniel Sabo">
 What is the proper way to submit a patch to wine? Do you need a 
 special password to use cvs commit or can you only mail in diffs?
 How do you make a propper diff (yeah, I'm really new at this)?
 If someone could just add the needed 'fi' to the end of tools/winelauncher.in
 I'd be happy too :).</quote></p>

<p>Eric Pouech told him to go check out <a href="http://www.winehq.org">
www.winehq.org</a> for instructions.  Bill Medland actually went into detail
and suggested:</p>
<quote who="Bill Medland"><p>

	This is the way that I do it.</p>
	<p>
	My .cvsrc file specifies<br /><code>
	cvs -z 3<br />
	update -Pd<br />
	diff -u</code></p>
	<p>
	The -u on the diff is important.
	</p><p>
	Then I sit just below the "wine" on my machine and, for example for all the
	changes in the documentation directory, I do
	cvs diff wine/documentation &gt; diff.txt
	</p><p>
	I then edit diff.txt (actually I number my diff files for my convenience)
	and add my name and email address at the top and then the description of the
	change.  At the same time I check that the diff file makes sense.
	</p><p>
	If I wer a good boy I would then test the patch against a clean local copy
	of the code, using "<code>patch --dry_run</code>"
	</p><p>
	Finally I email in the diff file to wine-patches.
</p></quote>






</section>  





<section
  title="Borland Style Imports"
  subject="Resolving already resolved ordinal for Borland style imports"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/10/0013.html"
  posts="3"
  startdate="10/03/2001"
  enddate="10/03/2001"
>

<p>Uwe Bonnes was having some problems with dlls loading.  He provided
some debugging info and explained:</p>
<quote who="Uwe Bonnes"><p>
  	some programm using a dll with Borland style imports crashes if the dll is
	loaded a second time. When PE_fixup_imports is called for the first time,
	resolving goes fine.
	</p><p>
	Now ordinal is replace by the function pointer in PE_fixup_imports. 
	The second PE_LoadLibraryExA however goes astray, as it tries to 
	resolve the function pointer as an ordinal in PE_fixup_imports.
	</p><p>
	What is the right solution? Only treat the value as an ordinal if it is
	smaller than 0x10000 (I suspect that a dll may only have 0xffff entries or
	the IMAGE_SNAP_BY_ORDINAL wouldn't work)? Or is it an error that we call
	PE_fixup_imports for the second time at all for an already resolved dll?
	</p></quote>

<p>Fixup is the process by which a DLL loaded into memory
has its executable image changed to take into account the difference between
it's base address and actual load address.  
Alexandre replied that fixup should never be done twice to
a DLL.  Uwe asked for help at this point because he couldn't figure out how to
inhibit that behavior.</p>

</section>





<section
  title="DDEConnect Errors"
  subject="DdeConnect errors while running setup.exe"
  archive="http://www.winehq.org/hypermail/wine-devel/2001/09/0165.html"
  posts="2"
  startdate="09/30/2001"
  enddate="10/01/2001"
>

<p>Ian Stewart was having a problem loading a program on his daughter's
computer.  He described what he was trying to do:</p>
<quote who="Ian Stewart"><p>
  Due to resource constraints (75 MHz processor, 1.2 GB hard drive, 16 MB
  RAM), we recently replaced Windows98 on our daughter's PC with Linux
  Mandrake, using the IceWM window manager.  It isn't quite as flashy as
  Windows, but it boots beyond the startup screen, which is more than can be
  said for Win98.
 </p><p>
  Well, to make a long story short, I've installed and configured Wine
  following the instructions in the Wine User's Guide.  Everything seems to
  be working properly, but when I attempted to run the setup.exe for 'Jim
  Henson Muppets Letters: Capital and Small', I received the following errors:
 </p>
 <p><code>
        err:ddeml:DdeConnect .. but no Server window available<br/>
        err:ddeml:DdeClientTransaction Invalid conversation handle<br/>
        err:ddeml:DdeClientTransaction Invalid conversation handle<br/>
        err:ddeml:DdeClientTransaction Invalid conversation handle<br/>
        fixme:ddeml:DdeUninitialize16  stub calling DdeUninitialize<br/>
 </code></p>
 <p>
  Following the recomendations in the Wine User's Guide, section 3.2
  (Installing Wine Without Windows), I re-ran wine with --debug msg
  +module,+file.  I didn't see anything in the trace that jumped out at me,
  but I've attached it here, just in case it means something to someone else.
 </p><p>
  One last thing.  The setup.exe appears to be a 16-bit app, originally
  designed for Windows 3.1.  Not sure if that makes any difference or not.
 </p><p>
  Any help in resolving this would be greatly appreciated.
 </p></quote>

<p>Eric Pouech replied that DDEConnect currently did not work between two
different processes.</p>

</section>


</kc>
