<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.bluesata.com">Zachary Goldberg</author>
<issue num="342" date="3/3/2008" />
<intro> <p>This is the 342 issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to  It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="39" size="66" contrib="15" multiples="7" lastweek="12">

<person posts="11" size="20" who="ono at java.pl (Adam Strzelecki)" />
<person posts="7" size="9" who="dmitry at codeweavers.com (Dmitry Timoshkov)" />
<person posts="4" size="8" who="winehacker at gmail.com (Steven Edwards)" />
<person posts="3" size="3" who="dank at kegel.com (Dan Kegel)" />
<person posts="2" size="5" who="truiken at gmail.com (James Hawkins)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="fgouget at free.fr (Francois Gouget)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="m.b.lankhorst at gmail.com (Maarten Lankhorst)" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="jim at pagesmiths.com (Jim White)" />
<person posts="1" size="3" who="stefan at codeweavers.com (Stefan =?utf-8?q?D=C3=B6singer?=)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="stefan at codeweavers.com (Stefan D&#246;singer)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="jjmckenzie51 at sprintpcs.com (James McKenzie)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="austinenglish at gmail.com (Austin English)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="wine-devel at kievinfo.com (Vitaliy Margolen)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="juan.lang at gmail.com (Juan Lang)" />

</stats>

<section
	title="News - Summer of Code approaches"
	subject="Google Summer of Code"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2008-February/062921.html"
	posts="1"
>
<topic>GSoC</topic>
<p>
Google recently announced their spec. for Google Summer of Code 2008 and the Wine community did not miss a beat.  Kai Blin, Wine's GSoC coordinator was on the ball with the following announcement:
</p>
<quote>
<p>
Hi folks,
<br />
Google announced the 2008 programme today and I wanted to use the opportunity
to talk about the next steps we should take to get ready.
<br /><br />
I will start a separate thread to start collecting project ideas, presenting
the ones mentioned on the wiki page [1]. New project ideas are very much
welcome. If any of you feels like mentoring one of the projects, please
mention that. If you're a student with your own project idea, please mention
that as well.
<br /><br />
We will then have to discuss if we believe the projects are doable in a Summer
of Code timeframe. When we talked about last year's projects on WineConf, it
was the common opinion that we didn't do a very good job on that for 2007. I
don't have a surefire solution for this, we should try being a bit more
conservative though.
<br /><br />
I will add some more documentation to the SoC wiki page, does anybody have a
good idea what we could call the post-mortem analysis? I know this is a
correct technical term, but in my opinion it sounds a bit negative. Lacking a
better alternative, I'd call it review. Can the native speakers come up with
something else?
<br /><br />
Maarten, you wrote a wiki page about your 2007 experience. Could you add it to
the "Helpful Links" section?
<br /><br />
[1] <a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/SummerOfCode">http://wiki.winehq.org/SummerOfCode</a>
<br /><br />
Cheers,<br />
Kai
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Maarten Lankhorst is also looking for volunteers:
</p>
<quote>
<p>Hi all,
<br /><br />
I'm planning on being administrator for wine project with the summer
of code 2008.
</p><p>
I'm looking for mentor volunteers. If you don't know what that is read
take some time to read through
<a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/faqs.html">http://code.google.com/soc/2008/faqs.html</a>
If anyone is interested, please contact me privately.
</p><p>
I'm also looking for project ideas, if anyone has an idea for a
project for the summer of code, please update
http://wiki.winehq.org/SummerOfCode . I would prefer projects that can
be done by small changes at a time, like implementing changes to get
an application to work, instead of something dractic like a dib
engine. It should preferably be doable in 2 to 3 months by someone who
doesn't have a lot of wine experience yet.
</p><p>
I'm also looking for people who want to help out in other ways, like
updating the wiki page and creating some additional information that
would be useful to students.
</p><p>
Cheers,<br />
Maarten.
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Its funny, both Maarten and Kai end thier emails with 'Cheers' hence, the logical conclusion is that they are both good folk!
</p>
<p>
Kai Blin also made a large post of project ideas.  Some of which are summarized below, however if you're interested please check out <a href="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2008-February/062923.html">the full thread</a> on this topic.
</p>
<quote>
<p>
 * Implementing a WinePluginApi so other programs can use Windows DLLs inside
of Linux apps
</p><p>
* Improving our HTML/Win32 Help viewers.
</p><p>
* Implementing the ASIO audio infrastructure for Cubase
</p><p>
* Implement the MS Wsock dll (dlls/mswsock), an enhanced winsocket
implementation
</p><p>
* Valgrind and Wine integration (see: Wine_and_Valgrind)
</p><p>
* Complete the Wine Web browser (aka. Internet Explorer) ie. frame controls,
toolbar, status bar
</p><p>
* Full URLMoniker implementation. (IE working with builtin urlmon.dll)
</p><p>
* Implement transacted mode for OLE32 Storage (STGM_TRANSACTED)
</p><p>
* Improve cmd.exe compatibility
</p><p>
* Get Mozilla compiling as a Winelib application
(http://www.winehq.org/site/winelib#mozilla)
</p><p>
* Run the Mauve Java test suite against Sun's Windows JRE, and file bugs /
write test cases in C / fix anything it finds
</p><p>
* Run the MDAC conformance test suite against Microsoft's MDAC, and file
bugs / write test cases in C / fix anything it finds
</p><p>
* pick some real-world app or game that doesn't work well, and improve Wine so
it installs and runs the app better. (Some good examples might be Photoshop,
Visual Basic, a game etc)
</p><p>
* pick a Windows feature that is incomplete in Wine, and improve the feature
and its conformance tests. (Some good examples might be riched20, DirectPlay,
etc)
</p>
</quote></section>
<section
	title="Wine patches into valgrind"
	subject=""
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2008-February/062460.html"
	posts=""
>
<topic></topic>
<p>
A lot of work has gone into making Wine and Valgrind play nice and produce useful output together.  There has been an external patch set which was recently committed upstream.  Dan Kegel:
</p>
<quote>
<p>
Hey, the Valgrind developers finally merged the Wine
support patches!  I just built Valgrind from svn as
described here:
<a href="http://valgrind.org/downloads/repository.html">http://valgrind.org/downloads/repository.html</a>
and on a fresh install of Gutsy, it just worked, no patches.
</p><p>
To run Valgrind's tests under Wine, I configure valgrind with
--prefix=/usr/local/valgrind-svn, then do something like
</p><p>
<code>
cd wine-git/tools
wget http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/runtests.patch
wget http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/valgrind-daily.sh
wget http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/valgrind-suppressions
wget http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/valgrind-split-pl.txt -O valgrind-split.pl
patch -p2 &amp;lt; runtests.patch
</code>
Then to run all the tests, I do
</p><p><code>
cd ~/wine-git
sh tools/valgrind-daily.sh
</code>
</p><p>
or to run just one test, I do
<code>
 export RUNTEST_USE_VALGRIND=1
 cd ~/wine-git/dlls/riched20/tests
 make test
</code>
I've only verified that this works well on one machine so far, but
I have high hopes.  Anyone else feel like giving it a whirl?
-Dan
</p>
</quote></section>
<section
	title="A Wine vs. Vista comparison"
	subject="Wine"
	archive="http://wastingtimewithmikeandari.wordpress.com/2008/01/31/linux-has-better-windows-compatibility-than-vista/"
	posts="3"
>
<topic>Comparisons</topic>
<p>
An <a href="http://wastingtimewithmikeandari.wordpress.com/2008/01/31/linux-has-better-windows-compatibility-than-vista/">article</a> was posted recently with an interesting comparison of running several Windows XP games on Windows Vista and on Linux with Wine with some fairly interesting results.  Take some of this with a grain of salt; the author does sound a tad biased.  Some excerpts:
</p>

<quote>
<p>
Soldat on Wine:<br />
The default configuration does not work, but unlike in Vista, when Soldat crashes, it doesn't bring the entire operating system down with it - the process just terminates. To get it to work, I have to turn all the settings way down, but it works... slowly.
</p>
<p>
Darwinia on Wine:<br />
Again, its shocking to see better application compatibility on Wine than in an actual version of Windows. Although Darwinia fails to run in Vista unpatched, it runs fine under Wine (even at a tolerable speed)
</p>
<p>
Conclusion:<br />
This post is clearly a bit biased. What shocked me though was how easy it was to find games that didn't run under Vista but did in Linux by using Wine or DOSBox. I'm not a huge gamer, so I don't have a huge collection of games to try out, but even still with just a few hours of frustrating work, I have been able to show that not only is Linux a reasonable alternative to Vista for gaming (XP is still king though), but also that Linux handles application failures more gracefully than Vista. Every game but Blackthorne crashed my Vista box, this didn't happen a single time under Linux.

</p>

</quote></section>
<section
	title="Taking Wine out of userspace?"
	subject="Wine"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2008-February/063048.html"
	posts="5"
>
<topic>Wine</topic>
<p>
Call me a total geek but when I first read this thread I got really excited.  The basic premise of the <a href="http://www.reactos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5240">reference project</a>, called the "Linux Unified Kernel" is to use wine to natively support many standard windows system calls, effectively taking much of Wine out of userspace and into kernel land.  Dan Kegel's brief explanation:
</p>
<quote>
<p>
It looks like they added hooks to the linux kernel
to accept windows nt syscalls.  Maybe they even allow using the
system's normal shared library loader instead of Wine's
special one.  This is something I've often wanted to do, but it was way lower priority
than getting wine working.  I haven't looked at their
project at all, no idea if it was done well.

</p>
</quote>
<p>
There are some obvious benefits to this (some speed improvements being some) and some obvious pitfalls (this becomes very linux-only whereas now Wine currently supports Linux, BSD and Mac).  I was a bit concerned that such a project would never take off due to lack of upstream (Kernel) acceptance.  However, Dan Kegel apparently has some insider info which floored me:
</p>
<quote>
<p>
We would, I think, like to move wineserver into the kernel
sometime.  It's been discussed before.  Linus is not
opposed to having native support for win32 system calls.
A fellow at Redhat wrote a kernel module for wine a number
of years ago, but it just wasn't time yet.
<br /><br />
For a related BSD thingy, see
http://www.kernel-traffic.org/wine/wn20010313_87.html#1
That project was still going as of 2006, I think, but didn't
get terribly far.
<br /><br />
- Dan
</p>
</quote>
<p>
And there you have it; an interesting project that, should it do well, may change the way we use Wine in the future.
</p></section>
<section
	title="Several Big Applications now working in Wine!"
	subject=""
	archive=""
	posts=""
>
<topic></topic>
Visual studio and something else, check starred.</section>
<section
	title="iTunes progress, gooo Maarten!"
	subject=""
	archive=""
	posts=""
>
<topic></topic>
Maarten lankhorst doing well...</section>
<section
	title="Weekly AppDB/BugZilla Status Changes"
	subject="AppDB/BugZilla"
	archive="http://appdb.winehq.org"
	posts="0"
>
<topic>AppDB / BugZilla</topic>
<center><b>BugZilla Changes:</b></center>
<p>
<i>
*Temporary Disclaimer: For the better part of the month of January Wine's bugzilla will be going through an annual triage and cleanup.
While the following statistics are still meaningful, (perhaps even moreso than otherwise) they are very skewed from normal Wine BugZilla activity.
</i>
</p>
<p>
<center>
<table border="1" bordercolor="#222222" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
  <tr>
  <td align="center">
	<b>Category</b>
  </td>
  <td>
         <b>Total Bugs Last Issue</b>
  </td>
  <td>
	<b>Total Bugs This Issue</b>
  </td>
  <td>
	<b>Net Change</b>
  </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     UNCONFIRMED
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     1767
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     1781
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      +14
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     NEW
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     1474
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     1472
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      -2
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     ASSIGNED
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     45
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     45
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      0
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     REOPENED
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     79
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     77
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      -2
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     RESOLVED
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     641
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     714
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      +73
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td align="center">
     CLOSED
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     7697
    </td>
    <td align="center">
     7724
    </td>

    <td align="center">
      +27
    </td>
  </tr>

   <tr>
     <td align="center">
       TOTAL
     </td>
     <td align="center">
      11703
     </td>
     <td align="center">
      11813
     </td>
     <td align="center">
      +110
     </td>
   </tr>
</table>
</center>
</p>
<br />
<br />
<center><b>AppDB Application Status Changes</b></center>
<p><i>*Disclaimer: These lists of changes are automatically  generated by information entered into the AppDB.
These results are subject to the opinions of the users submitting application reviews.
The Wine community does not guarantee that even though an application may be upgraded to 'Gold' or 'Platinum' in this list, that you
will have the same experience and would provide a similar rating.</i></p>
<div align="center">
   <b><u>Updates by App Maintainers</u></b><br /><br />
    <table width="80%" border="1" bordercolor="#222222" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Application</b>
        </td>
        <td width="140"><b>Old Status/Version</b></td>
        <td width="140"><b>New Status/Version</b></td>
	<td width="20" align="center"><b>Change</b></td>
       </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1251">Stronghold 1.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.51)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9492">dBPowerAmp Music Converter Release 12</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.46)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=10382">Isobuster 2.3</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.52)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=2712">Star Wars: Knights of the Old Republic 1.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.46)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+4</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=10455">Battlefield Vietnam 1.2x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=443">Visual FoxPro 7</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=6803">Touhou Eiyashou ~ Imperishable Night 1.00d</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td colspan="3">
		Total Change
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
        </table>

  <br />   <b><u> Updates by the Public </u></b> <br /><br />
   <table width="80%" border="1" bordercolor="#222222" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Application</b>
        </td>
        <td width="140"><b>Old Status/Version</b></td>
        <td width="140"><b>New Status/Version</b></td>
	<td width="20"><b>Change</b></td>
       </tr>


           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=8198">Tactical Ops: Assault on Terror 3.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.38)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9901">Team Fortress 2 - Steam February 19, 2008</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.51)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=5779">Project64 1.6</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=6199">Bridge Baron 14</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.22)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1744">Worms Armageddon 1.0-3.6.28.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9846">Proteus 7.2</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=3472">Mathematica 5.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.44)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.54)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=4102">Age of Empires II The Conquerors Expansion: Demo</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.20)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.51)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=402">Electronics Workbench 5.12</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.25)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=6297">TOCA Race Driver 3 1.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=7160">Acrobat 8.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=5288">Magic ISO 5.3</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.41)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1565">SimCity 4 1.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.53)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9194">Guild Wars All Versions</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.55)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9243">EndNote X1</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.51)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=4278">.NET Framework 1.1</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=8265">Voyage Century 0.39 (+old v1.21 upgraded)</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.45)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=10839">Sins of a Solar Empire 1.02</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.55)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=7190">PhotoImpact 12</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=5777">The Elder Scrolls IV: Oblivion 1.1.511</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9854">Need for Speed: ProStreet 1.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1303">Acrobat 5.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.42)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1554">Steam All Versions</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.52)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=10521">Warhammer 40,000: Dawn of War Soulstorm: DEMO</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.55)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=4525">Silent Hill 2 1.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=10429">Call of Duty 4: Modern Warfare 1.4</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.53)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=3927">IMVU BETA</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=2720">Halo: Combat Evolved 1.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.54)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.56)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=7453">CPU-Z 1.39</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.55)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>

           <tr>
             <td colspan="3">
		Total Change
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+15</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
        </table>

</div>
  </section>
</kc>
