<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<kc>

<title>Wine Traffic</title>

<author contact="http://www.bluesata.com">Zachary Goldberg</author>
<issue num="334" date="12/10/2007" />
<intro> <p>This is the 334 issue of the Wine Weekly News publication.
Its main goal is to introduce the new AppDB Status changer It also serves to inform you of what's going on around Wine. Wine is an open source implementation of the Windows API on top of X and Unix.  Think of it as a Windows compatibility layer.  Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available.   You can find more info at <a href="http://www.winehq.org">www.winehq.org</a></p> </intro>
<stats posts="140" size="227" contrib="63" multiples="26" lastweek="0">

<person posts="12" size="13" who="julliard at winehq.org (Alexandre Julliard)" />
<person posts="9" size="11" who="jjmckenzie51 at sprintpcs.com (James McKenzie)" />
<person posts="8" size="10" who="dank at kegel.com (Dan Kegel)" />
<person posts="7" size="9" who="stefan at codeweavers.com (Stefan D&#246;singer)" />
<person posts="6" size="11" who="winehacker at gmail.com (Steven Edwards)" />
<person posts="6" size="7" who="aric at codeweavers.com (Aric Stewart)" />
<person posts="5" size="23" who="zgold550 at gmail.com (Zachary Goldberg)" />
<person posts="5" size="6" who="truiken at gmail.com (James Hawkins)" />
<person posts="5" size="5" who="huw at codeweavers.com (Huw Davies)" />
<person posts="4" size="3" who="hverbeet at gmail.com (H. Verbeet)" />
<person posts="3" size="15" who="alex at thehandofagony.com (Alexander Nicolaysen Sornes" />
<person posts="3" size="7" who="gerald at pfeifer.com (Gerald Pfeifer)" />
<person posts="3" size="6" who="fgouget at free.fr (Francois Gouget)" />
<person posts="3" size="3" who="infyquest at gmail.com (Vijay Kiran Kamuju)" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="zac at zacbrown.org (Zac Brown)" />
<person posts="2" size="7" who="tzi063 at student.uib.no (Tomas Zijdemans)" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="mstefani at redhat.com (Michael Stefaniuc)" />
<person posts="2" size="3" who="frank.richter at gmail.com (Frank Richter)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="ngompa13 at gmail.com (King InuYasha)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="kai.blin at gmail.com (Kai Blin)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="jacek at codeweavers.com (Jacek Caban)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="stefandoesinger at gmx.at (Stefan D&#246;singer)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="thunderbird2k at gmx.net (Roderick Colenbrander)" />
<person posts="2" size="2" who="thestig at google.com (Lei Zhang)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="rob at codeweavers.com (Robert Shearman)" />
<person posts="2" size="1" who="dmitry at codeweavers.com (Dmitry Timoshkov)" />
<person posts="1" size="6" who="chmorgan at gmail.com (Chris Morgan)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="vostok at etersoft.ru (Anatoly Lyutin)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="alex at thehandofagony.com (Alexander Nicolaysen =?utf-8?q?S=C3=B8rnes?=)" />
<person posts="1" size="2" who="felix at compsoc.nuigalway.ie (Darragh Bailey)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="andrey.turkin at gmail.com (Andrey Turkin)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="alexd4 at inbox.lv (Alexander Dorofeyev)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="nessi at nessi-online.de (nessi at nessi-online.de)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="lav at etersoft.ru (Vitaly Lipatov)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="ben at atomnet.co.uk (Ben Hodgetts)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="ben at atomnet.co.uk (Ben Hodgetts (Enverex))" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="coke at lounge.lu (Gilles May)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="scott at open-vote.org (Scott Ritchie)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="chris.kcat at gmail.com (Chris Robinson)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="marius.slyzius at scimore.com (Marius Slyzius)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="hurtta+gmane at siilo.fmi.fi (Kari Hurtta)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="polleke at gmail.com (Paul van Schayck)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="ken at codeweavers.com (Ken Thomases)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="xerox_xerox2000 at yahoo.co.uk (Louis Lenders)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="Roy.Decoutere at pandora.be (Roy Decoutere)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="zgs at seas.upenn.edu (Zachary Goldberg)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="luis.busquets at ilidium.com (luis.busquets at ilidium.com)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="crwulff at rochester.rr.com (Chris Wulff)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="maarten at codeweavers.com (Maarten Lankhorst)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="gabriel.sailer at gmx.net (Gabriel Sailer)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="marcus at jet.franken.de (Marcus Meissner)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="the3dfxdude at gmail.com (Jesse Allen)" />
<person posts="1" size="1" who="brian.vincent at gmail.com (Brian Vincent)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="ripzonetriton at gmail.com (Triton)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="frick at sc-networks.de (Christoph Frick)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="patrol at sinus.cz (Pavel Troller)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="mihai.dontu at gmail.com (Mihai =?utf-8?q?Don=C8=9Bu?=)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="tom at dbservice.com (Tomas Carnecky)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="skrzynka365 at konto.pl (Piotr Maceluch)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="gav at transgaming.com (Gavriel State)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="kornelpal at gmail.com (=?iso-8859-2?B?S29ybulsIFDhbA==?=)" />
<person posts="1" size="0" who="luis.busquets at ilidium.com (=?ISO-8859-1?Q?=22Luis_C=2E_Busquets_P=E9rez=22?=)" />

</stats>

<section 
	title="News: Wine on the Linux Desktop"
	subject="Wine"
	archive="http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS8454912761.html"
	posts="0"
>
<topic>Wine on Linux</topic>
<p>
As you may have read the <a href="http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS8454912761.html">Annual Linux Desktop Survey Results</a> are in for the year.  Theres the usual bit about what browser people use and their favorite distribution.  However, the folk over at <a href="http://linuxdesktop.com">linuxdesktop.com</a> have also included some interesting information on how people run windows applications on Linux.  Their results can be summed up with the following text and chart:
<quote><p>
Of those that do, many turn to Wine (Wine Is Not an Emulator ), which runs the Windows API (application program interface) on top of Linux. More than 44 percent use Wine for their Windows applications needs.

I suspect that many Wine users actually use Wine with the help of programs that makes deploying Windows applications on Linux easier. However, of the two most important of these programs, Cedega, which specializes in running Windows games on Linux, and CrossOver, which focuses on Windows business and productivity applications, only 6 percent of our survey respondents said they used Cedega, while even less, 5 percent, said they used CrossOver.

<div align="center">
<a href="http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS9488592005.html"><img border="0" src="http://desktoplinux.com/files/misc/2007-windowsappsonlinux.jpg" /></a>
</div>
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Desktoplinux's Steven Vaughan-Nichols writes in a <a href="http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS9488592005.html"> separate  article</a> also highlights how linux users feel about applications:
<quote><p>
Given a choice of applications to run on their Linux desktops, most users would prefer to run a native Linux application rather than a Windows application. In particular -- Adobe take note -- Linux users continue to really want Linux versions of Adobe's Photoshop and Dreamweaver. These were numbers one and three on the Linux users' Windows application migration wish list. Autodesk's AutoCAD was number two.

If Linux users can't run a particular application on Linux, and there's no native program that gives them similar functionality, they're almost perfectly divided between three different methods to get them their required program. These are using WINE, or a software built on WINE, such as Crossover Linux, to run the Windows application in Linux; virtualization; and switching to a browser-based application, such as Google Docs.
</p></quote></p>
</p>
</section>
<section 
	title="Wine Review Blog"
	subject="Wine"
	archive="http://wine-review.blogspot.com/"
	posts="0"
>
<topic>WineReview</topic>
<p><a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/TomWickline">Tom Wickline</a> has begun a <a href="http://wine-review.blogspot.com/">"Wine-Review" blog</a>.  He writes about his experiences trying every windows application he can find on as many different platforms he can find. </p>
<quote><p>
<p>
The goal of the blog is to post about Wine (and to help people) on any
x86 operating system that Wine will run on e.g
Linux, BSD, X86 Mac, and even Solaris ...
</p><p>
The goal of the Forum is to to provide a place for people who are
interested in Wine to meet and collaborate about
there favorite applications and games. And to be a source for help and
suggestions.
</p></p></quote>
<p>
Tom's blog has done very well thus far; hes quoted to me that he estimates nearly 100,000 hits per month.  He is also seeking contributors to his blog.
</p>
<quote><p>
I plan to seek other contributors to the blog as well..... I cant own
every Office app or Game out there
and I currently don't own a Intel Mac. And whats surprising to me is i
received well over 2500 hits from
people who run Intel Mac's last month, even tho I don't currently post
about Wine on that platform.
</p></quote>
<p><div align="center">
<a href="http://bp0.blogger.com/_PpaJ8vsrkzo/R1erwTlKzII/AAAAAAAABDE/T8r-sHjsx6w/s1600-h/Screenshot-5.png"><img border="0" src="http://bp0.blogger.com/_PpaJ8vsrkzo/R1erwTlKzII/AAAAAAAABDE/T8r-sHjsx6w/s400/Screenshot-5.png" /></a>
</div></p>

</section>
<section 
	title="DiB Engine Status"
	subject="Code"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/060934.html"
	posts="2"
>
<topic>DiB Engine</topic>
<p>
<p>The DiB (Device Independent Bitmap) engine is one of the few remaining "large" issues that in general the community believes needs to be implemented.  The only issue with that is that implementing the DiB is actually very difficult.  At present WINE gets around having a DiB engine by translating the calls into something X can handle, lets X do the legwork and then translates the results back.  This is for the most part an effective solution, however its known to be inefficient and not without its problems.  Alex Juillard has expressed opinion that implementing a proper DiB engine will likely be done post 1.0.  See <a href="http://wiki.winehq.org/DIBEngine">the wiki page</a> on DiB for more information.</p>
<p>
In light of all this, Piotr Maceluch writes in to find out the current status of the DiB Engine.
</p>
<p><quote who="Piotr Maceluch">
<p>Hi,</p>
<p>what's the status of DIB engine (or where can one read about it)? Are the up-to-date sources still available? What kind of help would be needed?</p>
<p>
Thanks<br />
  Peter Maceluch
</p>
</quote></p>
<p>
Jesse Allen writes in with the status of his project:
</p>
<p><quote who="Jesse Allen"><p>
<p>
If you are talking about my project, it is still available, and I
merged up to a recent git snapshot two weeks ago.
http://repo.or.cz/w/wine/dibdrv.git
</p>
<p>
I can't promise too much until after finals. I'm going to work on it
and finish the image support during my break. Finishing the image
support and proper forwarding of the missing stuff is probably what is
needed to get it merged into wine.
</p>
<p>
If you need to have it merged up again, I will do that. If you want to
start hacking on it, pretty much any of the stubs you can work on.
<br />
Jesse
</p>
</p>
</quote>
</p>
</p>

</section>
<section 
	title="AppDB Switches to AGPL"
	subject="AppDB"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/060926.html"
	posts="9"
>
<topic>Licensing</topic>
<p>
<p>
Alexander S generated a bit of discussion a couple weeks ago when he introduced a change in the AppDB's license to the AGPL.  Of course a change of license like this requires the approval of all authors involved and so the list asked all authors for consent; it appears all confirm.
<br /><br />
<p>
Trent Waddington kicks it off recognizing that all authors need to approve:
<quote who="Trent Waddington"><p>
Interesting.  Do you have a list of contributors and their signoff on
this license change?
<br /><br />
Or is it just you two?
</p>
</quote></p>

<p>Alex then agrees, and asks all co-authors to confirm
<quote who="Alexander Sornes">
<p>
<p>
Well I didn't think that was necessary; but after some thought I realize that
the AppDB only seemed to include a LICENSE file containing the GPL v2, while
a GPL/AGPL v3 change would require previous code to be licenced under 'GPL v2
or later'.
</p>
<p>
So I'm including the other authors in this mail to see if they agree, or have
already licenced their code under GPL v2 or later
</p><p>
Sorry for all the mess, but legal stuff isn't really my thing. :)
</p>
<br />
Alexander N. Sornes
</p>
</quote>
</p>
</p>
<p>
One by one they give permission:
<quote>
<p>
Chris Morgan: <br />
I think I'm ok with the gpl/agpl v3 change. Are there any other people
using the appdb code that this might affect?
<br /><br />
Jonathan Ernst:
<br />
I'm ok with this change too.
<br /><br />
Paul van Schayck
<br />
Yup, I'm ok with that change.
</p></quote>
</p>

<p>
For those of you who appreciate such a thing, the following is the key difference between the GPL and AGPL (from <a href="http://www.affero.org/oagf.html">affero.org</a>)
<quote><p>
Section 2(d) reads as follows: " If the Program as you received it is intended to interact with users through a computer network and if, in the version you received, any user interacting with the Program was given the opportunity to request transmission to that user of the Program's complete source code, you must not remove that facility from your modified version of the Program or work based on the Program, and must offer an equivalent opportunity for all users interacting with your Program through a computer network to request immediate transmission by HTTP of the complete source code of your modified version or other derivative work."
</p></quote></p>
</p>

</section>
<section 
	title="New valgrind reports"
	subject="Valgrind"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/061007.html"
	posts="1"
>
<topic>Valgrind</topic>
<p>
Getting sick of having to run reports by hand, Dan Kegel writes in with information about his new <a href="http://valgrind.org/">valgrind</a> script.  Valgrind is a profiling tool used to help track memory leaks.  Wine developers regularly check for leaks and make all possible efforts to keep them to a minimum.
</p>
<quote who="Dan Kegel">
<p>
I finally got tired of doing "history | grep diff" etc, and
partially automated the daily valgrind run; the resulting
script is at <a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/valgrind-daily.sh">http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/valgrind-daily.sh</a>
</p>
<p>
The results are now in directories named like <br />
<a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/">http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/</a> <br />
<br />A summary of the new problems compared to last run are in files named like<br />
<a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06-summary.txt"> http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06-summary.txt</a><br />
<br />
And next to each individual result, there is a diff with the previous run, e.g. <br />
<a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/vg-oleaut32_varformat.txt">http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/vg-oleaut32_varformat.txt</a><br />
<a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/vg-oleaut32_varformat-diff.txt">http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06/vg-oleaut32_varformat-diff.txt</a><br />
</p>
<p>
To look at what changed since yesterday, start by looking at the day's
summary file.
In it, there's one line per test, followed by the changes in that
test's results, if any.
</p>
<p>
Lines that start with + indicate new problems (boo);<br />
lines that start with - indicate old problems that are now gone (yay!)<br />
Nearby lines that are identical except for one starting with + and one
starting with -
indicate a problem that moved, so ignore those.
</p>
<p>
For example, in today's summary, <br />
<a href="http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06-summary.txt">http://kegel.com/wine/valgrind/logs-2007-12-06-summary.txt</a>
the first test with changes is in hlink:<br />
diff -u logs-2007-12-05/vg-hlink_hlink.txt logs-2007-12-06/vg-hlink_hlink.txt <br />
- Syscall param write(buf) points to uninitialised byte(s)<br />
<br />
That means the hlink test has one fewer error.  Yay!
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Of course, while the new script is nice, its also git its kinks and things Dan would like to see improved/changed.
</p>
<quote><p>
I'll try to keep running this script daily, but it'd be nice if
somebody else took over (and possibly even increased
the automation; I still have to do git pull, run the script, and
upload by hand.)
</p><p>
It doesn't help that valgrind only works well on some machines,
but hey, what's life without challenges.
<br />
- Dan
</p>
</quote>
</section>
<section 
	title="Default Homepage in IE on WINE"
	subject="Homepage"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/060935.html"
	posts="9"
>
<topic>shdocvw.dll</topic>
<p>
On a bit of a lighter note there was some discussion on what WINE should set as its default homepage in IE.  It all began with the a patch from Jacek Caban which sets the default homepage to winehq.com  However, Aric Stewart was quick to point out the problem with the patch.
</p>
<quote who="Aric Stewart"><p>
I see that the native shdocvw sets neither the Start page nor the Search 
page when registered. This patch forces the users home page to initially 
be www.winehq.com which can be confusing to IE users who are expecting 
the normal default of msn.com
</p><p>
While amusing I do not think this is correct.<br />
-aric
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Steve Edwards writes in to second that opinion.
</p>
<quote><p>
Plenty of OEM's change the default IE home page, and we should make it
easy to do so in Wine. I think a edit box in winecfg is the best route
to go with the default option being about:blank or www.winehq.org
</p><p>
Thanks<br />
-- <br />
Steven Edwards<br />
</p>
</quote>
<p>
Jacek Caban tries to clarify the issue with his reasoning behind the patch in the first place.
</p>
<quote><p>
Native shdocvw.dll doesn't support self registration at all and its
registration is done by IE installer IMO. If we want to be compatible
with native, we'd have to move everything from shdocvw.inf to wine.inf
(and that's not the way to go IMO). I've added these registries because
an app I've been working on expected default search page to be present.
Also we should use it in our InternetExplorer and WebBrowser
implementation. We may consider to handle these keys like we do with IE
version key. That is, they may be added on iexplore.exe registration. If
one wants to install native IE, he has to unregister iexplore.exe first,
removing the homepage. Then IE installer will probably set its default
homepage.
</p></quote>
<p>Aric refutes:</p>
<quote><p>
Humm, maybe i am confused but (at least the win98 version of )
shdocvw.dll implements DllRegisterServer which seems to do a lot of
stuff.  But Setting the Start Page is not one of them.  In my experience
installing IE does not actually set a Start Page by default, but instead
the browser seem to handle not having a Start Page by pulling up a
default one.
</p></quote>
<p>
Jakek writes:
</p>
<quote><p>
I've checked it again and it looks like shdocvw registers only its
typelib, nothing else like coclasses. I will do more testing later today.
</p></quote>
</section>
<section 
	title="Wine Benchmarks"
	subject="Wine Benchmarking"
	archive="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/061035.html"
	posts="4"
>
<topic>Wine</topic>
<p>
In addition to the monumental task of implementing and replicating native behavior of the Windows API WINE has to also manage to do it with near-native speeds.  Phoronix has recently <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=938&amp;num=1">Benchmarked</a> a series of different wine versions.  Their results are indeed interesting and highlight the importance of remembering both of the goals WINE strives to achieve, compatibility and efficiency.
</p>
<p>Jonathan Ernst writes in to link wine-devel to the article</p>
<p><quote who="Jonathan Ernst"><p>
Hello,<br />
<br />
What do you think about their tests and results ?<br />
<br />
<a href="http://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=11539">http://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=11539</a>
</p>
<p>
"The performance in the fourteen 3DMark 2001 SE and 3DMark 2003 tests
were fairly consistent in the releases between WINE 0.9.44 and WINE
0.9.50 -- generally only swaying a few frames in either direction --
though the performance overall has slightly declined and we were
surprised by a few of the results."
</p>
<p>
I guess it's linked with <a href="http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=10631">http://bugs.winehq.org/show_bug.cgi?id=10631</a>
</p></quote></p>
<p>
Stefan Dosinger's take on this issue:
</p>
<quote><p>
No, it doesn't look like they are hit by the 3dmark2k1 bug, which is strange.
They are hit by the stencil test slowness in 3dmark2k3 though, which we
resolved as a driver bug on geforce 8 cards, since we couldn't reproduce it
elsewhere.<br />
<br />
I didn't find any info what card they used, so it is a bit hard to say what
might be wrong.
</p></quote>
<p>
Bryan Haskins think's its an 8-Series:
</p>
<quote><p>
Phoronix often uses the 8 series cards when not testing things like driver versions, we can probably assume they did use an 8 series.
</p></quote>
<p>
So the issue of why Phoronix obtained such odd results in .49 and .50 remains.  This is a good time however to discuss the <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=11539">bug</a> mentioned originally by Jonathan Ernst.   Indeed, this bug, related to a patch by Stefan Dosinger, seems to have stirred the hornet's nest of late.  The patch fixes some graphical glitches but introduced a couple cases in which performance was severely crippled.  Stefan however is working hard to fix these cases.
</p>
<p>
In reference to the same patch, Stefan <a href="http://www.winehq.org/pipermail/wine-devel/2007-December/061026.html">writes</a>:
</p>
<quote who="Stefan Dosinger"><p>
This patch caused quite a few similar regressions, I fixed one of them before
the .50 release, and another one afterwards, so you might want to give the
current git code a try. However, there is at least one (not yet known)
situation left where shaders recompile all over.
</p></quote>
</section>
<section 
	title="AppDB Application Status Changes"
	subject="AppDB"
	archive="http://appdb.winehq.org"
	posts="0"
>
<topic>AppDB</topic>
<p><i>*Disclaimer: This list of changes is automatically  generated by information entered into the AppDB.
These results are subject to the opinions of the users submitting application reviews.  
The WINE community does not guarantee that even though an application may be upgraded to 'Gold' or 'Platinum' in this list that you
will have the same experience and would provide a similar rating</i></p>
<div align="center">
   <b><u>Updates by App Maintainers</u></b><br /><br />
    <table width="80%" border="1" bordercolor="#222222" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
      <tr>
        <td> 
          <b>Application</b>
        </td>
        <td width="140"><b>Old Status/Version</b></td>
        <td width="140"><b>New Status/Version</b></td>   
	<td width="20" align="center"><b>Change</b></td>
       </tr>

           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9620">Serif PhotoPlus PhotoPlus 11</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif" style="color: #FFFFF;">
               Garbage (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=8842">TREPCAD 3.4.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif" style="color: #FFFFF;">
               Gold (0.9.46)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #990000;">-3</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9704">TTPlayer 5.0.1</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif" style="color: #FFFFF;">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9760">Touhou Fuujinroku ~ Mountain of Faith 1.00</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif" style="color: #FFFFF;">
               Garbage (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.50)
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=6090">X²: The Threat 1.4</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif" style="color: #FFFFF;">
               Garbage (0.9.32)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td align="center">
               <div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
             </td>
           </tr>
      
    </table>
  <br />   <b><u> Updates by the Public </u></b> <br /><br />
   <table width="80%" border="1" bordercolor="#222222" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Application</b>
        </td>
        <td width="140"><b>Old Status/Version</b></td>
        <td width="140"><b>New Status/Version</b></td>
	<td width="20"><b>Change</b></td>
       </tr>

 
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=7591">Battlefield 1942 1.6x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-4</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=8842">TREPCAD 3.4.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.46)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=2890">Half-Life 2 Retail (32-bit)</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.47)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+4</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=3781">Rollercoaster Tycoon 3 1.00</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.35)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=5819">Mozilla Firefox 2.0.0.11</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.42)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_platinumbg.gif">
               Platinum (0.9.49)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9760">Touhou Fuujinroku ~ Mountain of Faith 1.00</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=6090">X²: The Threat 1.4</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.32)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.49)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=5820">Real MYST 1.1.1 demo/test</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.21)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=4184">Age of Empires II The Conquerors Expansion: 1.0x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.46)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=8248">Safari 3.x Public Beta</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.46)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_bronzebg.gif">
               Bronze (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9704">TTPlayer 5.0.1</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.48)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=1251">Stronghold 1.x</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-1</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9620">Serif PhotoPlus PhotoPlus 11</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_goldbg.gif">
               Gold (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+3</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=4704">SPSS 13.0</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.38)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #990000;">-2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
           <tr>
             <td>
                <a href="http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?sClass=version&amp;iId=9865">WISO Sparbuch 2008</a>
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_garbagebg.gif">
               Garbage (0.9.49)
             </td>
             <td background="images/wwn_silverbg.gif">
               Silver (0.9.50)
             </td>
	     <td align="center">
		<div style="color: #000000;">+2</div>
	     </td>
           </tr>
    
      </table>
</div>
  </section>
</kc>
